<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <post author="JoAnne" timestamp="0002-11-30 00:00:00.0">
    <title>A Day in the Life</title>
    <sentence-list count="35">
      <sentence position="1" labelers="1, 2, 3">My family and friends are constantly trying to figure out just what it is that I do.</sentence>
      <sentence position="2">As noted in the comments on Clifford s recent post, our loved ones - loving as they are - just don t get it.</sentence>
      <sentence position="3" labelers="2, 4">They all seem to understand that we have accomplished something, but really don t have a clue as to what that something is, or even how we spend our time.</sentence>
      <sentence position="4">My best friend s husband summed it up best: Just what is it that you do during the day? he asked.</sentence>
      <sentence position="5">I tried to explain, but his eyes glazed over quickly.</sentence>
      <sentence position="6" labelers="1, 2, 4">I now have a neat one-liner, meant to answer such inquiries: I get paid to think.</sentence>
      <sentence position="7" labelers="2">For me, that seems to sum it up fairly well.</sentence>
      <sentence position="8" labelers="2">But now I ve got this blogging gig, and I can go into a little more depth.</sentence>
      <sentence position="9" labelers="2">I plan to do so in a series of posts, `A day in the life.</sentence>
      <sentence position="10" labelers="2, 3">In this series, I will list my activities for the day, in the hope that it will become more clear just how us academics spend our time.</sentence>
      <sentence position="11">I hope I don t bore you to death.</sentence>
      <sentence position="12" labelers="1, 3">Today was kind-of a ho-hum average day, so it seems like a perfect place to start.</sentence>
      <sentence position="13" labelers="4">First activity of the day (even before making coffee): Check email.</sentence>
      <sentence position="14">Answer email that came in overnight.</sentence>
      <sentence position="15">Check the blog.</sentence>
      <sentence position="16">Morning at work: Chat with co-workers.</sentence>
      <sentence position="17" labelers="1">Deal with referee reports: write a reply to answer a referee report on my latest paper, print out the large review article that I have been asked to referee (printer jammed several times, so the printing process took awhile), started to read another paper that I have been asked to referee - determined that they included all the correct Feynman diagrams contributing to their calculation.</sentence>
      <sentence position="18" labelers="3, 4">Started the required computer training course for supervisors on detecting sexual harassment (last week we determined that supervising graduate students counts as being an official lab/university supervisor).</sentence>
      <sentence position="19" labelers="1, 3">Talked at length on the phone with my former graduate student, and laid out the groundwork for a new project we are starting (I m quite excited about it!).</sentence>
      <sentence position="20">Filled out the paperwork to have my desktop monitor, which died last week, fixed or replaced.</sentence>
      <sentence position="21">Cleaned out my backpack (this was not trivial).</sentence>
      <sentence position="22" labelers="1">Read through the latest draft of responses to a set of questions posed by the EPP2010 panel about the future of high energy physics.</sentence>
      <sentence position="23">Continuous monitoring of email.</sentence>
      <sentence position="24" labelers="1">Noticed I had worked through lunchtime.</sentence>
      <sentence position="25">Had a discussion with my long-term associate Tom Rizzo on the Statistical Mechancis properties of TeV mass blackholes.</sentence>
      <sentence position="26">(This evening Tom sent some very interesting results he had computed for his new project!)</sentence>
      <sentence position="27" labelers="4">Left for home mid-afternoon to work on my ongoing deck staining project.</sentence>
      <sentence position="28" labelers="3">Stained 32 feet of railing (slats every 6 inches!) before darkness fell.</sentence>
      <sentence position="29">The deck has to get stained before it cools down and the rains start.</sentence>
      <sentence position="30" labelers="4">Watched the NOVA special on Einstein s Big Idea and saw the stuff missing from our special sneak preview at SLAC.</sentence>
      <sentence position="31">Just before bed: post on the blog.</sentence>
      <sentence position="32">Check email one last time.</sentence>
      <sentence position="33">This was just an average day for any academic.</sentence>
      <sentence position="34">No epiphanies, no frustrated calculations, no nonsensical answers from computer code.</sentence>
      <sentence position="35" labelers="3, 4">Just the average, day-to-day grind work that us academics deal with.</sentence>
    </sentence-list>
  </post>
  <comment-list count="15">
    <comment id="1" author="Plato" timestamp="2005-10-12 03:05:00.0">Have you ever talk to Giddings? If this possibility is true, the most remarkable prediction of this scenario is that black holes could be created at high-energy accelerators, perhaps as early as with the LHC. We studied this problem of black hole creation and decay carefully, and came to the conclusion that there could be a lot of black holes made (up to around one per second) and that they could apparently produce very outstanding effects in the detectors at the LHC. This possibility has obviously aroused a lot of interest. http://www.esi-topics.com/blackholes/interviews/SteveGiddings.html Yep, it does mine.</comment>
    <comment id="2" author="JoAnne" timestamp="2005-10-12 03:43:00.0">Plato, yep, I find the possibility of blackholes at the LHC very interesting.  Check out my paper from last Spring: BLACK HOLES IN MANY DIMENSIONS AT THE LHC: TESTING CRITICAL STRING THEORY.By JoAnne L. Hewett, Ben Lillie, Thomas G. Rizzo (SLAC),. SLAC-PUB-11024, Mar 2005. 5pp.e-Print Archive: hep-ph/0503178</comment>
    <comment id="3" author="Torbjorn Larsson" timestamp="2005-10-12 06:51:00.0">I think you succeeded in making your work day sound ordinary enough. Except that you do some work _before_ making coffee!</comment>
    <comment id="4" author="Jay" timestamp="2005-10-12 09:08:00.0">I&amp;#8217;m curious if you find the time spent to learning to &amp;#8220;detect sexual harassment&amp;#8221; worthwhile? Or, is it a distraction?</comment>
    <comment id="5" author="citrine" timestamp="2005-10-12 10:24:00.0">Are you teaching any classes? If so, how come you didn&amp;#8217;t spend any time grading? (Or do T.A.s do it for you?)</comment>
    <comment id="6" author="JoAnne" timestamp="2005-10-12 11:40:00.0">Jay, for me the sexual harassment course was a bit of a distraction (especially at 2 hours long!).  I&amp;#8217;m fairly well attuned to such things.  However, I can personally vouch that there are some people who need the training - badly. Citrine, SLAC has a funny status.  It is both a school within Stanford University (same as, say, the school of engineering), and a national laboratory.  We have a faculty (of which I&amp;#8217;m a member) that are professors at Stanford Unversity.  However, in practice we are really a lab, so we are research oriented and generally don&amp;#8217;t teach.  Once in awhile we&amp;#8217;ll teach a special topics course on some aspect of high energy physics.  I did so last Winter quarter.  That was the third quarter I&amp;#8217;ve taught in the 12 years I&amp;#8217;ve been here. The fact that we don&amp;#8217;t teach makes what we do even more mysterious to people.  Everybody can understand teaching, and assumes that either we teach or we sit around twiddling our thumbs.</comment>
    <comment id="7" author="Arun" timestamp="2005-10-12 16:08:00.0">You&amp;#8217;re lucky - you get paid to think.  In the Dilbertesque world of the large American corporation, one is often paid to suspend one&amp;#8217;s ability to think. Examples available on request.</comment>
    <comment id="8" author="Tom Renbarger" timestamp="2005-10-12 19:18:00.0">I&amp;#8217;ll be interested to see what you&amp;#8217;ll have after you&amp;#8217;ve written a few of these &amp;#8220;day in the life&amp;#8221; posts, JoAnne.  One of the things that tends to get lost in the shuffle is the nature of science as a process, as opposed to a collection of results (the way it is almost exclusively reported), and your project is exactly the sort of thing that can remedy this misperception.</comment>
    <comment id="9" author="Trackback  from Cosmic Variance" timestamp="2005-10-12 23:42:00.0">On Parents and Physicists First Clifford and then JoAnne have recently written about what their families think of them being physicists and whether they understand what it is their children actually do. These are interesting questions, not only because they explore the persona&amp;#8230;</comment>
    <comment id="10" author="Pingback  from What are the odds? | Cosmic Variance" timestamp="2005-10-13 01:28:00.0">[&amp;#8230;] Today, I continued on the deck staining project (as mentioned in a post yesterday). I needed a newspaper to put under the brushes and can of stain. Yesterday was recycle day, so I threw out all my old newsprint. Scouring the garage, I came across an old newspaper, still covered in plastic. I took it out of the plastic, picked a few pages at random from the middle and placed it under my can of stain. About an hour later, dipping my brush into the can, I saw a headline staring out at me:   Bloggers Learn the Peril of Posting Too Much Information [&amp;#8230;]</comment>
    <comment id="11" author="Aaron F." timestamp="2005-10-16 20:58:00.0">Great post!!! I&amp;#8217;ve always wondered what theoretical physicists and mathematicians do all day. I mean, if you&amp;#8217;re an experimentalist or an engineer, you can fiddle with machinery and analyze data and such&amp;#8230; but I can&amp;#8217;t imagine getting paid to sit around and think. What if you couldn&amp;#8217;t think of anything? I&amp;#8217;d feel so guilty&amp;#8230;</comment>
    <comment id="12" author="citrine" timestamp="2005-10-17 20:01:00.0">Aaron, According to the mathematician Erdos, a mathematician is a machine that turns coffee into equations. I&amp;#8217;d say that this is true of many theoretical physicists as well.</comment>
    <comment id="13" author="Clifford" timestamp="2005-10-17 20:12:00.0">Aaron F. If you can&amp;#8217;t think of something, you find out what others are thinking. In other words, you read a paper, read a book, go to a seminar, (check a blog), ichat or call a colleague and ask a question, etc. Pretty soon, you&amp;#8217;ve got new stuff to chew on and useful thoughts spurt out all over the place. Cheers, -cvj</comment>
    <comment id="14" author="JoAnne" timestamp="2005-10-18 12:41:00.0">Aaron F:  Indeed new ideas just tend to sprout, as Clifford spelled out.  I never have the time to work on all of them and have to pick and choose. Citrine:  Indeed the caffiene factor is most joked about.  However, at least at SLAC, many of us are caffiene-free (for medical reasons due to previous mistreatments of the powerful drug).  So coffee is not a factor.</comment>
    <comment id="15" author="Pingback  from Another day in the life | Cosmic Variance" timestamp="2005-11-30 18:48:00.0">[&amp;#8230;] Here at Cosmic Variance we occasionally grant the gawking masses a brief glimpse into the glamorous and sexy world of the professional physicist. So, for those of you keeping score at home, I just did a quick count: in the last 24 hours I have sent 35 emails. Sadly, I have received 54 emails, so it looks like I&amp;#8217;m still falling behind. (No, this doesn&amp;#8217;t include spam &amp;#8212; I usually get between 100 and 150 of those per day, but I do have a very good spam filter.) [&amp;#8230;]</comment>
  </comment-list>
</page>

