<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <post author="Clifford" timestamp="2006-03-23 07:53:00.0">
    <title>A Spectacular Breakdown of the Law of Averages</title>
    <sentence-list count="36">
      <sentence position="1">So I was on a flight from LA to Chicago a short while ago.</sentence>
      <sentence position="2" labelers="1">The usual thing happened, at first: I was on the plane early, and watching my fellow passengers get on the plane and go by, finding their seats.</sentence>
      <sentence position="3" labelers="3">There s that situation that happens on all forms of public transport that you ll all recognize: You re secretly hoping that you ll sit next to a beautiful and interesting woman (or man, depending upon your preferences), but instead, she never shows up.</sentence>
      <sentence position="4" labelers="1">Instead, that guy (and it s always that same guy isn t it!!?) who s a bit too large for the seat, and who leaks into yours even though he s supposed to be in the seat next to you.</sentence>
      <sentence position="5">(This happens on buses, trains, planes, whereever. Always that same guy.)</sentence>
      <sentence position="6">So, yes, this happened.</sentence>
      <sentence position="7">Fine, I was used to it.</sentence>
      <sentence position="8">But then something unexpected happened.</sentence>
      <sentence position="9" labelers="1, 3">The guy next to him (on the other side) asked him if he d mind swapping seats with his friend in another seat so that they could sit together, and he agreed.</sentence>
      <sentence position="10">And guess what?</sentence>
      <sentence position="11" labelers="1, 3">The friend turned out to be a striking young French woman with cute almost elfin features.</sentence>
      <sentence position="12">This turn around was quite a shock to me.</sentence>
      <sentence position="13" labelers="1">Anyway, not being one for harrassing people just because they re attractive, I carried on with my business of getting ready for the flight, and then started reading some sheets of paper, which happened to be covered in equations and diagrams.</sentence>
      <sentence position="14">My usual airplane reading, I must report.</sentence>
      <sentence position="15">(Often it is the best place to think about research no distractions . no phones, email, blog, students, colleagues etc. They re going to spoil that all soon by the way.)</sentence>
      <sentence position="16">Well, anyway, a while into reading, my striking neighbour spoke up with -of course- the perfect French accent to match, and said Er, excuse me, are you a teacher of Mathematics?.</sentence>
      <sentence position="17">I explained that indeed I teach and Mathematics is part of what I teach, alongside Physics .etc.</sentence>
      <sentence position="18">Er, at a University or School?.</sentence>
      <sentence position="19">University.</sentence>
      <sentence position="20" labelers="1">She brightened up considerably, and explained that she loved Mathematics and Physics and studied them for a while at University.</sentence>
      <sentence position="21" labelers="1, 2, 3, 4">So at that point I was thinking that the Law of Averages had spectacularly broken down today on two counts .</sentence>
      <sentence position="22" labelers="2, 3, 4">One: Beautiful and interesting women never end up sitting next to me in such situations;</sentence>
      <sentence position="23" labelers="2, 3, 4">Two: People who learn what I do never say that they love it and have studied it, but usually trot out the I was never good at physics/maths at school line ..</sentence>
      <sentence position="24" labelers="2">So having been given license to ask at least two questions in return, I asked where she studied these things.</sentence>
      <sentence position="25">Paris VI.</sentence>
      <sentence position="26" labelers="2">And then I asked what her line of work is now.</sentence>
      <sentence position="27" labelers="2, 4">She wanted to do something different, and so even though she loves physics and mathematics, she decided to leave France and ..join the circus.</sentence>
      <sentence position="28">Yes, you read that right.</sentence>
      <sentence position="29">She is a circus performer.</sentence>
      <sentence position="30">She is in fact an acrobat.</sentence>
      <sentence position="31" labelers="1, 2, 3, 4">So .Law of Averages breakdown number three: How many times do you actually meet someone who ran away to join the circus?!</sentence>
      <sentence position="32">-cvj P.S.</sentence>
      <sentence position="33">Nope, I did not propose marriage on the spot.</sentence>
      <sentence position="34" labelers="3">Look, can you imagine the employment two-body problem involved with one person a theoretical physicist and the other a trapeze artist?</sentence>
      <sentence position="35" labelers="3">Oh, and yes, another reason was her boyfriend sitting on the other side of her.</sentence>
      <sentence position="36">It was a red-eye flight, so I gave her my cough sweets (she had a cold) and I turned over and went to sleep.</sentence>
    </sentence-list>
  </post>
  <comment-list count="29">
    <comment id="1" author="John Doe" timestamp="2006-03-23 08:48:00.0">Is the law of averages really braking down? What you described happens to me all the time&amp;#8230; not&amp;#8230; but indeed it happened once, and with striking similarities.I was on a  TGV on my way to Paris to give a talk when a striking woman takes a seat next to me,  as I open my laptop to rework one last slide (something to do with TE cross-correlation) she asks me about my line of work, I apologize for my very pour French and I attempt an explanation at which she replies in practically perfect English. It turned out she was from Lebanon, working in advertising, we had a wonderful few hours conversation. As we said goodbye we exchanged email addressees, and here were the similarities became creepy: a year later I received an email telling me that she moved to Canada where she was working PR for Cirque du Soleil.</comment>
    <comment id="2" author="adam" timestamp="2006-03-23 09:16:00.0">And now, after all these years, the Gallic &amp;#8220;acrobats stalk physicists across the world&amp;#8221; plot has been exposed. The cunning devils. Be alert!</comment>
    <comment id="3" author="Kieran" timestamp="2006-03-23 09:17:00.0">Check to see if your wallet and credit cards are still where they should be. Maybe also your kidneys. Just a suggestion.</comment>
    <comment id="4" author="adam" timestamp="2006-03-23 09:20:00.0">Good point on the kidneys. Clifford&amp;#8217;s so cool that he is used to awaking surrounded by ice, so he could have missed out on the odd missing organ.</comment>
    <comment id="5" author="adam" timestamp="2006-03-23 10:12:00.0">It&amp;#8217;s clear that what we have uncovered here is a Gallic Circus Plot to construct a Superclown from stolen physicist parts.</comment>
    <comment id="6" author="JustAnotherInfidel" timestamp="2006-03-23 10:32:00.0">You should have at least got her phone number.</comment>
    <comment id="7" author="adam" timestamp="2006-03-23 10:51:00.0">Yeah, he could just have asked her boyfriend for it. If he was too shy to ask her.</comment>
    <comment id="8" author="Andrew" timestamp="2006-03-23 10:56:00.0">By the way, I&amp;#8217;m always at a loss for what to say in response to the &amp;#226;&amp;#8364;&amp;#339;I was never good at physics/maths at school&amp;#226;&amp;#8364;&amp;#65533; thing. What are your ideas? Ideally, it would come across as humble and charming, while at the same not completely dispelling any mystique I might have picked up by saying I study math and physics.</comment>
    <comment id="9" author="adam" timestamp="2006-03-23 11:04:00.0">Tell them it&amp;#8217;s not as difficult as being beautiful must be. Sure, you&amp;#8217;ll crash and burn, but then, you&amp;#8217;re going to anyhow. Best to go down laden with cheese.</comment>
    <comment id="10" author="Jeff Hodges" timestamp="2006-03-23 11:24:00.0">Andrew: I&amp;#8217;ve crafted a half-way decent response to the Physics face.</comment>
    <comment id="11" author="Supernova" timestamp="2006-03-24 00:57:00.0">I have somewhat the opposite problem:  people tend to be overly excited when they find out I&amp;#8217;m an astronomer, often to the point of ignoring or even subtly denigrating other people in the conversation.  My husband calls it the &amp;#8220;That&amp;#8217;s nice&amp;#8221; effect, in reference to all the times that someone we&amp;#8217;ve just met, after waxing poetic about how much they loved astronomy as a kid, has asked him what he does and, on hearing &amp;#8220;rhetoric&amp;#8221; has responded, &amp;#8220;Oh, that&amp;#8217;s&amp;#8230; nice&amp;#8230;&amp;#8221; (once even, &amp;#8220;It&amp;#8217;s good that someone&amp;#8217;s doing that&amp;#8221;). What bothers me even more is the people who think that those of us who study physics/astronomy must be inscrutable geniuses far beyond the comprehension of most mere mortals.  Last time I went to DC for an NSF review panel, I stayed in a very nice B&amp;amp;B run by a wonderful friendly woman who nonetheless let me eat breakfast every morning in silent solitude because (I eventually discovered) she figured I&amp;#8217;d rather be left alone with my grand thoughts than socialize with someone like her.  As someone who believes such attitudes are a big part of physics&amp;#8217; PR problem and largely our fault to begin with, I found this truly dismaying and obsessed for days over what I might have said or done to seem arrogant or dismissive.  We have a long way to go in this culture struggle!</comment>
    <comment id="12" author="citrine" timestamp="2006-03-23 13:17:00.0">Yeah, those of us in Physics/ Math have it pretty bad when it comes to answering the inevitable &amp;#8220;what do you do&amp;#8221;? However, I think we have it over the beleaguered souls who have dedicated a significant portion of their lives to pursuits such as &amp;#8230;.ummmm &amp;#8230;. Gyneacology and Proctology. Also, I wonder what kind of responses Morticians get when they announce their line of work?</comment>
    <comment id="13" author="Plato" timestamp="2006-03-23 15:17:00.0">Mortician&amp;#8230;..maybe just shoot the breeze and ask what kind of sabersaw he has, or any other kind of implements of the trade that he might use? As far as genius&amp;#8217;s go, skill&amp;#8217;s of the trade, maybe? &amp;#8220;They&amp;#8221; (is large population presented) can certainly do other things. Joanne, the drain engineering, or &amp;#8220;painting the deck&amp;#8221; by Clifford.  Chef&amp;#8217;s capabilities let&amp;#8217;s not forget. Where&amp;#8217;s the degree? So &amp;#8220;reverse scenario&amp;#8221; that the lawn guy &amp;#8220;is&amp;#8221; actually interested in flowers and plants, then the science of the person? Naw! The &amp;#8220;pizza guy&amp;#8221; and Sean always comes to mind. They/I, mean well. Have the same deeper motivaton about life? People are no different no matter what kind of &amp;#8220;hat&amp;#8221; they wear? Right? Or, are they? Careful, least I show you Math/physics people are human too</comment>
    <comment id="14" author="adam" timestamp="2006-03-23 15:51:00.0">This is all beside the point. If they build a Superclown, who knows what will happen? It could be the End Of The World.</comment>
    <comment id="15" author="Sourav" timestamp="2006-03-23 15:58:00.0">Rare events are common. And, I take offense to being characterized as a &amp;#8220;leaky&amp;#8221; airline passenger &amp;#8212; those seats are designed for anorexic midgets from the 1970s!</comment>
    <comment id="16" author="Plato" timestamp="2006-03-23 16:25:00.0">President of OWA I presume? I never thought of it like that before adam. Scary:) Rival to King KOng holding the beautiful girl while being shot at? Larger then life, primitive emotions kind of thing?</comment>
    <comment id="17" author="JustAnotherInfidel" timestamp="2006-03-23 16:30:00.0">You could always tell people you&amp;#8217;re a gay porn star, and then say &amp;#8220;Nah I&amp;#8217;m just kidding&amp;#8230;I&amp;#8217;m actually a theoretical physicist.&amp;#8221; I&amp;#8217;m just sayin&amp;#8230;it&amp;#8217;s worked before.</comment>
    <comment id="18" author="adam" timestamp="2006-03-23 16:33:00.0">If they made it from physicist parts it could have Absence of Social Graces superpowers, for a start. Like Dick Cheney with a smiley painted face and intent on Unifying the Fields in order to achieve Total World Domination.</comment>
    <comment id="19" author="Elliot" timestamp="2006-03-23 16:42:00.0">You could always say you are writing a play/screenplay  about mathemeticians physicists and are doing research and you just happen to have a character that is an attractive french woman.</comment>
    <comment id="20" author="Clifford" timestamp="2006-03-23 17:18:00.0">John Doe (comment #1):- In fact, they were returning to Canada (Montreal), which is where she&amp;#8217;d moved to from France, and I assumed it was Cirque du Soleil, but did not ask. Hmmmmm, maybe they are agressively recruiting physicists indeed! Sourav:-  I&amp;#8217;ve never met you (unless you&amp;#8217;re that guy). I was talking about that guy, (or the collective ones I&amp;#8217;ve encountered) and nobody else. Adam:- &amp;#8220;Better to go down laden with cheese&amp;#8230;.&amp;#8221;&amp;#8230;. LOL! Cheers, -cvj</comment>
    <comment id="21" author="Pingback  from Sleepless in Louisville | Cosmic Variance" timestamp="2006-03-23 17:20:00.0">[&amp;#8230;] Sean       &amp;#171; A Spectacular Breakdown of the Law of Averages &amp;#160;&amp;#160;&amp;#160;&amp;#160; [&amp;#8230;]</comment>
    <comment id="22" author="Sourav" timestamp="2006-03-23 17:48:00.0">Clifford, Sorry if my facetiousness was not apparent.  However, I am frustrated by narrow coach seating &amp;#8212; my shoulders don&amp;#8217;t fit. (We have not met, but I did enjoy D-Branes.) Best, Sourav</comment>
    <comment id="23" author="Plato" timestamp="2006-03-23 18:03:00.0">Maybe Sourav you could commet sometime on the Cerenkov radiation and what is expected from ICECUBE? thanks</comment>
    <comment id="24" author="Arun" timestamp="2006-03-23 21:57:00.0">Clifford, I think the law of averages doesn&amp;#8217;t work in your case, whether it be in the bus or on the plane.</comment>
    <comment id="25" author="AstroCook" timestamp="2006-03-23 23:35:00.0">I would leave it to you to find the non-average things in a seemingly average life, though.  many people would ignore such treats.  =) I just remember the story you told about the young girl on the bus.  Most people might just ignore that sort of thing!  Props.   =)</comment>
    <comment id="26" author="Clifford" timestamp="2006-03-24 12:20:00.0">AstroCook:- Thanks! -cvj</comment>
    <comment id="27" author="Samantha" timestamp="2006-03-24 16:26:00.0">#17  This has actually happened to me.  I was at a fancy dress party (hosted by my house-mate, a physicist), and was chatting to some chap in chains and asked him (politely) what he had come as.  A blue movie star, he said.  I said (wisely) ah, and what do you do in real life?  There was an awkward silence and he said, well I&amp;#8217;m a (gay) blue movie star.  And there was nothing, nothing  I could say to that.  Nothing.</comment>
    <comment id="28" author="Brunsli" timestamp="2006-03-29 12:38:00.0">Clifford, You haven&amp;#8217;t changed.  I miss your overly-analytical outlook on life.</comment>
    <comment id="29" author="Clifford" timestamp="2006-03-29 12:40:00.0">I miss it too. -cvj</comment>
  </comment-list>
</page>

