<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <post author="Clifford" timestamp="0002-11-30 00:00:00.0">
    <title>Painfully Funny</title>
    <sentence-list count="46">
      <sentence position="1" labelers="1">Pure genius.</sentence>
      <sentence position="2" labelers="1, 2, 3, 4">You have to listen to the 9th May edition of the live phone-in Down The Line!</sentence>
      <sentence position="3" labelers="1, 3">At some point I had to shut my office door, as I was laughing so much but trying not to be too loud so ended up with tears streaming down my face.</sentence>
      <sentence position="4" labelers="1, 2, 3">This week s topic: Religion, and Korean scientists discovery of a new colour.</sentence>
      <sentence position="5" labelers="1">Make sure you re not operating heavy machinery, or driving fast, before you listen.</sentence>
      <sentence position="6">(I don t know if there is an archive, so you might have to listen to it before they replace it with next week s edition.)</sentence>
      <sentence position="7" labelers="2">Example exchange (~22nd minute):</sentence>
      <sentence position="8">Host: Who s next?</sentence>
      <sentence position="9">I ve got Muhammed, from Birmingham.</sentence>
      <sentence position="10">Hello!</sentence>
      <sentence position="11">Guest (strong Brummie accent):</sentence>
      <sentence position="12">Hello.</sentence>
      <sentence position="13">Host: Now I don;t want to jump to any conclusions, Muhammed, but are you perhaps a Muslim?</sentence>
      <sentence position="14">Guest: That s right.</sentence>
      <sentence position="15">Host: Right. So what do you want to talk about?</sentence>
      <sentence position="16" labelers="3, 4">Guest: Well, I m ringing about this new primary colour</sentence>
      <sentence position="17" labelers="4">Host: Can I say We re also talking today about religion, and it s great to have a Muslim on the phone.</sentence>
      <sentence position="18">Guest: Yes.</sentence>
      <sentence position="19">Host: And I wonder if you could perhaps talk about what it s like being a Muslim in this day and age .</sentence>
      <sentence position="20" labelers="1">Guest: Oh, right. Yeah. I don t wanna talk about that. I ve rung up about the primary colour.</sentence>
      <sentence position="21">Host: But it s interesting isn t it ?</sentence>
      <sentence position="22">Do you find that there is a lot of er, intolerace towards you, and do you find that people look at your in a different way, .. than they used to, say, pre-9/11?</sentence>
      <sentence position="23">Guest: But what they gonna call this colour? That s what I wanna know, cos</sentence>
      <sentence position="24">Host: But</sentence>
      <sentence position="25">Guest: You know, like, when I was young .</sentence>
      <sentence position="26">Host: Listen</sentence>
      <sentence position="27">Guest: .they told me that you had blue, red, and green, or blue, red, and yellow</sentence>
      <sentence position="28">Host: that s right .</sentence>
      <sentence position="29">Guest: Depending upon whether you e doing Art or whether you e doing Physics .</sentence>
      <sentence position="30" labelers="3">Host: I don t think that people at home understand, neccessarily, what Islam means .</sentence>
      <sentence position="31" labelers="3">Guest: Well, I don t know really, cos everyone s different, but . how can you name a colour?</sentence>
      <sentence position="32">Host: Never mind about colours ..!!</sentence>
      <sentence position="33" labelers="2">It goes on like this for a while .</sentence>
      <sentence position="34">Brilliant.</sentence>
      <sentence position="35" labelers="2">Example exchange (~27th minute):</sentence>
      <sentence position="36">Host: Hello, you re through to Down the Line, Hello?</sentence>
      <sentence position="37">Guest (woman s voice; polite well-meaning tone):</sentence>
      <sentence position="38">Hello, I just wanted to say People seem very quick to judge the Muslims, but I think that we should wait a while, because you never know, they might come good .</sentence>
      <sentence position="39">Host: Hmmmm</sentence>
      <sentence position="40">Guest: My son, for example.He used to be a right little terror .</sentence>
      <sentence position="41">Host: Hmmm</sentence>
      <sentence position="42">Guest: now, he s a successful painter .</sentence>
      <sentence position="43">Host: Well thank you very much for your call!</sentence>
      <sentence position="44" labelers="1, 2, 3">And then the next one with the dog just had me rolling on the floor.</sentence>
      <sentence position="45" labelers="2, 3">I can t even describe it ..</sentence>
      <sentence position="46">-cvj</sentence>
    </sentence-list>
  </post>
  <comment-list count="22">
    <comment id="1" author="Matt B." timestamp="2006-05-09 20:46:00.0">This is hilarious. Thanks!</comment>
    <comment id="2" author="boreds" timestamp="2006-05-10 02:08:00.0">Yes, very informative.</comment>
    <comment id="3" author="boreds" timestamp="2006-05-10 02:28:00.0">The Lord is not aware of individuals in the rock business!</comment>
    <comment id="4" author="Wolverine" timestamp="2006-05-10 02:42:00.0">The complaints posted about the program are a scream too. Great stuff.</comment>
    <comment id="5" author="erc" timestamp="2006-05-10 06:34:00.0">That&amp;#8217;s great! And since I was sitting on the floor when it came on, I was literally ROFL when the dog bit came on. Wolverine - I read the complaints on the message board, and I have a theory: the people posting are the same ones who do phone into &amp;#8220;Any Answers&amp;#8221;. I just wish Jonathan Dimbleby would respond as appropriately as Gary Bellamy, for example &amp;#8220;You&amp;#8217;re just going round in circles&amp;#8221;, &amp;#8220;Oh god&amp;#8230;&amp;#8221;, &amp;#8220;You&amp;#8217;re not really going anywhere with this, are you?&amp;#8221;.</comment>
    <comment id="6" author="Daveg" timestamp="2006-05-10 07:47:00.0">Hmmm very strange indeed! It&amp;#8217;s a loony bin out there isn&amp;#8217;t it?</comment>
    <comment id="7" author="anon" timestamp="2006-05-10 08:15:00.0">Oh, this is brilliant. Thanks!</comment>
    <comment id="8" author="Simon" timestamp="2006-05-10 08:37:00.0">HAHAHAHA!!!! Magik</comment>
    <comment id="9" author="PK" timestamp="2006-05-10 09:55:00.0">The dog owner is hilarious! Close second for me is the London cabbie (he must be) in the beginning: &amp;#8220;My fairy tale is better than yours!&amp;#8221; and &amp;#8220;I can&amp;#8217;t hear ya lov.&amp;#8221; I honestly don&amp;#8217;t know whether there are planted phone calls in there, it all sounds very real and to some extent plausible.</comment>
    <comment id="10" author="boreds" timestamp="2006-05-10 10:56:00.0">Ummm.</comment>
    <comment id="11" author="Elliot" timestamp="2006-05-11 00:28:00.0">Now this is just plain scary. Look at the picture of the show&amp;#8217;s host. Then go to Lubos&amp;#8217;s site and look at his picture. It&amp;#8217;s frightening. Coincidence? You be the judge. Elliot</comment>
    <comment id="12" author="Esoth" timestamp="2006-05-10 15:32:00.0">Always with the stillness. . . Unless, of course, your dog is barking, in which case it is always with the SHUT IT!  WILL YOU SHUT IT!!!!. . . .</comment>
    <comment id="13" author="Clifford" timestamp="2006-05-10 15:37:00.0">Ah&amp;#8230;yes&amp;#8230;. the stillness&amp;#8230;.. Brilliant. Oh, gosh, just a mention of the dog cracks me up all over again&amp;#8230;. -cvj</comment>
    <comment id="14" author="Joe" timestamp="2006-05-10 19:01:00.0">For what it&amp;#8217;s worth, they archive the shows. Its a new show, so only 3 are listed on the left hand side. The BBC seem to be pretty good at keeping archives available.</comment>
    <comment id="15" author="Clifford" timestamp="2006-05-10 19:22:00.0">Thanks Joe. That was (frustratingly) not always the policy in the past, and so I&amp;#8217;m glad to hear that  this is now the norm. Cheers, -cvj</comment>
    <comment id="16" author="Joe" timestamp="2006-05-10 19:36:00.0">I&amp;#8217;m just listening to it now, and it seems pretty clear that it was set up. There is no way you could get that many oddballs in a row.</comment>
    <comment id="17" author="donncha" timestamp="2006-05-11 23:50:00.0">Uproar! http://media.guardian.co.uk/site/story/0,,1773143,00.html</comment>
    <comment id="18" author="Pingback  from Gullible of Tunbridge Wells | Cosmic Variance" timestamp="2006-05-12 02:48:00.0">[&amp;#8230;] Oddly enough, a huge number of people really thought that the utterly hilarious show Down the Line (see here), airing on Tuesdays at 11:00pm on the BBC&amp;#8217;s Radio 4, was actually a real phone-in! Rather than seeing it as a wonderful spoof, parody, and commentary (which it clearly is), they thought it was a crass attempt by Radio 4 to broaden the scope of its programming. Angry of Tunbridge Wells got out the pen and paper to write a letter&amp;#8230;&amp;#8230; [&amp;#8230;]</comment>
    <comment id="19" author="Clifford" timestamp="2006-05-12 02:54:00.0">Joe&amp;#8230; Where did you say the older programme is? There&amp;#8217;s nothing listenable under the link for the older episode. It is like the old days where the new epidose of a programme erases the old. Can you find it? -cvj</comment>
    <comment id="20" author="Joe" timestamp="2006-05-12 07:12:00.0">Hi Clifford. It looks like I made a mistake, sorry for getting your hopes up.</comment>
    <comment id="21" author="Pingback  from Thinking Aloud: The Pulpmovies Weblog &amp;#187; They go out and kill each other for their fairy stories" timestamp="2006-05-14 15:39:00.0">[&amp;#8230;] (via Cosmic Variance)    Posted by Paul in Religion and Superstition, TV and Radio&amp;#160;(14/5/2006 at 9:38 pm) [&amp;#8230;]</comment>
    <comment id="22" author="Pingback  from Stander on the Mountain &amp;#187; Blog Archive &amp;#187; BBC Radio" timestamp="2006-05-24 16:09:00.0">[&amp;#8230;] This Guy has much more interesting things to say about it, but this 'phone in' show is friggin' hilarious!! [&amp;#8230;]</comment>
  </comment-list>
</page>

