<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <post author="JoAnne" timestamp="2005-08-24 00:00:00.0">
    <title>The Road to Aspen</title>
    <sentence-list count="30">
      <sentence position="1">I have recently arrived in Aspen!</sentence>
      <sentence position="2" labelers="1">While Clifford was flying back to California from Aspen, I was driving the route in the opposite direction.</sentence>
      <sentence position="3" labelers="1">Took me 2 days to traverse the 1200 miles compared to Clifford s 2 hours of airtime.</sentence>
      <sentence position="4">Bottom line for the reader: continual blogging from Aspen by the CosmicVariance team.</sentence>
      <sentence position="5" labelers="1, 2, 3">I always find driving across America to be entertaining and enlightening and I never fail to learn new things about my country.</sentence>
      <sentence position="6">(Well, there is Nebraska but even that has the giant cattle pens and the Great Platte River Road Monument.)</sentence>
      <sentence position="7" labelers="1">The route from California to Colorado through the Western desert is simply beautiful, if not slightly endless.</sentence>
      <sentence position="8" labelers="4">We were treated to some rather wild (and rare) desert thunderstorms.</sentence>
      <sentence position="9">There was the standard Americana, giant plastic statues of cowboys and the like, and the far-flung Western towns such as Ely, Nevada consisting of a hotel, a gun shop, and a railroad depot.</sentence>
      <sentence position="10" labelers="3, 4">My personal favorite was the Shoe Tree - a lonely cottonwood on the side of Highway 50 with hundreds of pairs of shoes dangling from its branches.</sentence>
      <sentence position="11" labelers="1, 2">There are, of course, scary bits as well.</sentence>
      <sentence position="12" labelers="1">One 10-mile stretch in Nevada had large black spots on the highway.</sentence>
      <sentence position="13">At first they looked like pieces of a blown tire - then we noticed they were moving!</sentence>
      <sentence position="14" labelers="1">Closer inspection revealed the biggest, nastiest looking insects that I have ever seen.</sentence>
      <sentence position="15" labelers="2, 3, 4">Insects large enough to be discerned from a car traveling at 90 mph!</sentence>
      <sentence position="16">They were for sale, encased in glass, for $10 in the motel lobby in Utah and are known as Mormon Crickets.</sentence>
      <sentence position="17" labelers="2">The scariest bit was a letter to the editor in a local smalltown Utah newspaper.</sentence>
      <sentence position="18" labelers="2">You guessed it, the author was promoting Intelligent Design.</sentence>
      <sentence position="19">This line bothered me the most:</sentence>
      <sentence position="20" labelers="2, 3, 4">The atheistic scientists are ill-informed and are becoming the flat-worlders of the 21st century.</sentence>
      <sentence position="21">Flat-worlders!</sentence>
      <sentence position="22">I felt personally insulted!</sentence>
      <sentence position="23" labelers="3, 4">It seems that since I have data on my side in my scientific belief in evolution, the ID folks have to resort to name calling as a counter argument.</sentence>
      <sentence position="24">Name calling is a standard debate tactic, of course, and succeeds all too often in my view.</sentence>
      <sentence position="25" labelers="2, 3, 4">This single line, however, demonstrates the complete breakdown of scientific education in this country.</sentence>
      <sentence position="26" labelers="3">I wish this letter was just one more piece of harmless Americana .but I fear much worse.</sentence>
      <sentence position="27" labelers="1">Anyway, I am here for the Collider Physics Workshop, of which I am a co-organizer.</sentence>
      <sentence position="28" labelers="4">This is going to be great fun: 3 weeks of stimulating physics with 60-70 fellow collider folks in a beautiful atmosphere.</sentence>
      <sentence position="29">Simultaneously a 2-week workshop on the physics, detectors, and accelerator for the International Linear Collider is being held at Snowmass, Colorado, which is only 10 miles down the road from Aspen.</sentence>
      <sentence position="30">I will post more on this later.</sentence>
    </sentence-list>
  </post>
  <comment-list count="21">
    <comment id="1" author="Simon DeDeo" timestamp="2005-08-23 13:23:00.0">Perhaps the writer was referring to spatial flatness?</comment>
    <comment id="2" author="Clifford" timestamp="2005-08-23 15:47:00.0">90 mph? Naughty. -cvj</comment>
    <comment id="3" author="Gordon Chalmers" timestamp="2005-08-23 15:52:00.0">I really like the AI though.</comment>
    <comment id="4" author="hack" timestamp="2005-08-23 16:14:00.0">&amp;#8220;The atheistic scientists are ill-informed and are becoming the flat-worlders of the 21st century.&amp;#8221; Apparently he&amp;#8217;s confusing scientists with Tom Friedman.</comment>
    <comment id="5" author="JoAnne" timestamp="2005-08-23 16:56:00.0">Actually, my top speed (according to the GPS) was a bit more than 90 mph&amp;#8230;.</comment>
    <comment id="6" author="Richard" timestamp="2005-08-23 17:58:00.0">It&amp;#8217;s nice to read the comments of another Great Basin traveler on US 50. This is one of the great roads of North America. The Shoe Tree is a great grassroots work in progress and worth contributing to. I am going to guess that the pic on the lower right was taken on I-70 near Green River. I live in a small Utah town, Moab, that is emphatically not like the rest of Utah. While most of the folks around here recognize ID for the intellectual load of crap it is, it is still disturbing that in the 21st century evolution on every level (stellar, biological, computer automata, etc) is seen as controversial. Stop by on your way home.</comment>
    <comment id="7" author="Clifford" timestamp="2005-08-23 18:07:00.0">JoAnne: Shhh! I&amp;#8217;m not sure you&amp;#8217;re publicly supposed to be admitting to speeding !Oh, of course, you mean 90 using that number system that starts at 25, right? Ah! -cvj</comment>
    <comment id="8" author="spyder" timestamp="2005-08-23 18:48:00.0">Summer thunderstorms in the Great Basin region of the US are part of the monsoonal patterns that occur as moisture from both the Gulf of Mexico and the Pacific Coast off Baja/Mexico is pushed north by the various troughs of low pressure that also just happen to form, or have been formed by, those dastardly season hurricanes.  Desert thunderstorms in the Summer are not rare, but can be exceedingly dangerous. Wasn&amp;#8217;t that 90 kph??? so she could be driving along and taking pictures??</comment>
    <comment id="9" author="Moshe Rozali" timestamp="2005-08-23 18:48:00.0">cvj, Canadian cars would do the job, I normally go over 90 on the highway.</comment>
    <comment id="10" author="Clifford" timestamp="2005-08-23 19:48:00.0">Moshe&amp;#8230;I&amp;#8217;m pretty sure that most people do&amp;#8230;. 90 is not very high, especially on long open roads cross country. I used to do cross country a lot, so&amp;#8230;.. Anyway, I was just trying to leave some doubt, in case JoAnne runs for president one day  and the dirt-diggers find archives of the post and this comment thread! -cvj</comment>
    <comment id="11" author="Sean" timestamp="2005-08-23 20:00:00.0">I suspect that Moshe was referring to the common use in Canada of units known as &amp;#8220;kilometers,&amp;#8221; in which doing 90 is no big deal.  They still use the blatantly non-decimal &amp;#8220;hours,&amp;#8221; though, so I don&amp;#8217;t see why they&amp;#8217;re so pleased with themselves.</comment>
    <comment id="12" author="Moshe Rozali" timestamp="2005-08-23 20:12:00.0">Sean, Just trying to salvage the aforementioned presidential campaign, chances are she&amp;#8217;ll be competing with a Bush.</comment>
    <comment id="13" author="Sean" timestamp="2005-08-23 20:25:00.0">Associating with Canadians would be a greater electoral liability than being caught speeding.</comment>
    <comment id="14" author="Clifford" timestamp="2005-08-23 20:26:00.0">I think they&amp;#8217;re pleased because they&amp;#8217;re the nicest people on the planet! More or less. -cvj</comment>
    <comment id="15" author="Clifford" timestamp="2005-08-23 20:27:00.0">Careful Sean&amp;#8230;.. &amp;#8220;They&amp;#8217;re in our midst&amp;#8221;. Some may even read this blog&amp;#8230;..no&amp;#8230;I go too far! -cvj</comment>
    <comment id="16" author="JoAnne" timestamp="2005-08-23 23:58:00.0">So, you are saying that I shouldn&amp;#8217;t mention the radar detector that may (or may not) have been hooked up??</comment>
    <comment id="17" author="Clifford" timestamp="2005-08-24 12:03:00.0">On balance, best to leave that out, I would say. You have your voters to think about. More traffic-cop beating paraphenalia in the car equals more babies to kiss. Not good. -cvj</comment>
    <comment id="18" author="JoAnne" timestamp="2005-08-24 12:12:00.0">Richard, I&amp;#8217;ve been to Moab (gateway to Arches National Park) and found it to be a great town!  And yes, you have demonstrated excellent knowledge of Utah scenery - that pix is indeed from the rest stop on I-70 just before mile marker 180, just east of Green River.</comment>
    <comment id="19" author="Fyodor" timestamp="2005-08-24 12:33:00.0">By the way, I see that everyone here seems to think that Aspen is, without qualification, a great place. But one has heard some rather unpleasant stories about the atmosphere there, along the lines sketched in Magueijo&amp;#8217;s book &amp;#8212; attempted theft of ideas, etc. Any confirm/denies?</comment>
    <comment id="20" author="Clifford" timestamp="2005-08-24 12:42:00.0">Many needlessly inflammatory things were said in that book. It sells books. Does not mean that they have anything to do with reality. I don&amp;#8217;t know what he said about Aspen&amp;#8217;s atmosphere, but if it is as you say, then that is sad. I&amp;#8217;ve been to several places to do physics all over the country and all over the planet. Aspen is in the very top bracket of great places to do physics. I speak as someone who&amp;#8217;s been there many times. Did he say how many times he&amp;#8217;s been? Maybe he had a misunderstanding there and extrapolated (as autobiographers are wont to do), thus sacrificing some accuracy. All by accident, I imagine. -cvj</comment>
    <comment id="21" author="JoAnne" timestamp="2005-08-24 14:13:00.0">I don&amp;#8217;t know Magueijo&amp;#8217;s book, but I can confirm that Aspen is a great place to do physics.  I have never experienced any unpleasant situations here.</comment>
  </comment-list>
</page>

