<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <post author="Sean" timestamp="2006-06-23 00:51:00.0">
    <title>The Eleven-Mile Atomic Web Page</title>
    <sentence-list count="21">
      <sentence position="1" labelers="1, 2, 4">A web page presenting a scale-model hydrogen atom (via Cynical-C):</sentence>
      <sentence position="2" labelers="1">And you thought there was a lot of empty space in the solar system.</sentence>
      <sentence position="3" labelers="1, 3, 4">Well, there s even more nothing inside an atom.</sentence>
      <sentence position="4" labelers="1, 3">A hydrogen atom is only about a ten millionth of a millimeter in diameter, but the proton in the middle is a hundred thousand times smaller, and the electron whizzing around the outside is a thousand times smaller than THAT.</sentence>
      <sentence position="5">The rest of the atom is empty.</sentence>
      <sentence position="6" labelers="1">I tried to picture it, and I couldn t.</sentence>
      <sentence position="7">So I put together this page - and I still can t picture it.</sentence>
      <sentence position="8">The page is scaled so that the smallest thing on it, the electron, is one pixel.</sentence>
      <sentence position="9">That makes the proton, this big ball right next to us, a thousand pixels across, and the distance between them is yep, fifty million pixels (not a hundred million, because we re only showing the radius of the atom. ie: from the middle to the edge).</sentence>
      <sentence position="10" labelers="1">If your monitor displays 72 pixels to the inch, then that works out to eleven miles - making this possibly the biggest page you ve ever seen.</sentence>
      <sentence position="11" labelers="2">Okay, we all know that, science-wise, this is utterly bogus.</sentence>
      <sentence position="12" labelers="1, 2, 3, 4">Mostly because the proton and electron are not little spheres of fixed size, as our classical intuitions inevitably imagine them to be they should be represented by wavefunctions, and the electron s wavefunction in particular should be spread throughout all eleven miles.</sentence>
      <sentence position="13" labelers="2, 3">Admittedly, an eleven-mile web page that accurately represented the ground-state wavefunction of the hydrogen atom would have been harder to construct (although, hmm, maybe not impossible).</sentence>
      <sentence position="14" labelers="4">And I m not sure where the sizes of the particles came from.</sentence>
      <sentence position="15" labelers="2, 4">The proton really does have a size, about 1.5 x 10-15 m, since it s a bound state of quarks.</sentence>
      <sentence position="16" labelers="2, 3, 4">But the electron is a point particle, as far as we know.</sentence>
      <sentence position="17" labelers="1, 2, 3, 4">There are various distance scales you can associate to it, but the smallest of these is the classical electron radius, which is about twice the size of the proton diameter.</sentence>
      <sentence position="18">John Baez explains.</sentence>
      <sentence position="19" labelers="3">I don t know how to get an electron to be one thousandth the size of a proton, unless you re using masses rather than lengths, which is a big mistake because (in the wacky world of quantum mechanics) lengths get smaller when masses get bigger.</sentence>
      <sentence position="20">Still, it gives you some feeling for the instubstantiality of matter, as Geiger and Marsden long ago demonstrated.</sentence>
      <sentence position="21">And it s pretty cool.</sentence>
    </sentence-list>
  </post>
  <comment-list count="14">
    <comment id="1" author="quasar9" timestamp="2006-06-22 14:49:00.0">Sean, it does make you think. Dimensions, density, mass and gravity.Anyway previous comment I made gone AWOL. Thought it would go with this post on hydrogen atom. Shall I resubmit? or just redirect to link: http://quasar9.blogspot.com/  -Q.</comment>
    <comment id="2" author="Sean" timestamp="2006-06-22 14:59:00.0">quasar, you should really not repost your blog entries here at all; that&amp;#8217;s what trackbacks are for.  We&amp;#8217;ll readily delete comments that distract from the main conversation.</comment>
    <comment id="3" author="quasar9" timestamp="2006-06-22 16:01:00.0">Hi Sean, thanks. Just thought I&amp;#8217;d double check it wasn&amp;#8217;t actually an electronic glitch. Anyway great post. It is a relative perspective on dimension &amp;#8220;more nothing inside a hydrogen atom&amp;#8221;. Anyway for those with time to read more, the comment is on the blog. Address on previous comment. Enjoy! - Q</comment>
    <comment id="4" author="Alejandro Rivero" timestamp="2006-06-22 16:58:00.0">In this context it is interesting to remark that Copernicus argued for the vacuum space in the planetary model of the solar system by comparing it to the vacuum space in the atomic model of matter.</comment>
    <comment id="5" author="Trackback  from See you at Enceladus" timestamp="2006-06-22 17:04:00.0">A Bit of Ego Stroking, and a Lot of Modesty That Skeptic's Circle and link from Uncertain Principals (thanks!) really drove traffic here! At last count (5:00 PM -ish) there were 109 visits to Enceladus. I hoped you enjoyed it.Now that I done some ego stroking, lets all have a dose of modest&amp;#8230;</comment>
    <comment id="6" author="Science" timestamp="2006-06-22 17:18:00.0">Sean, Electrons are supposed to be Planck sized strings, according to certain people?  Also, that Planck thought he had got the smallest fundamental unit of length (plus time, etc) by dimensional analysis? Later it was discovered that a much smaller size exists, the black hole radius/even horizon radius.  Naturally the ignorant still use the Planck size.  (It is convenient for them, as there is no implied physical mechanism for the Planck size which there is for the black hole size, such as trapped electromagnetic energy.  I think the stringy people are deliberately steering as far away from simplicity/causality as possible.  Hence extra dimensional hype.)</comment>
    <comment id="7" author="Troublemaker" timestamp="2006-06-22 19:54:00.0">Copernicus used an analogy to a theory that didn&amp;#8217;t exist until centuries after his death?  How cool! [rolls eyes]</comment>
    <comment id="8" author="Pyracantha" timestamp="2006-06-22 22:49:00.0">They are using a photo of the planet Neptune as the &amp;#8220;proton&amp;#8221; sphere.</comment>
    <comment id="9" author="Joe" timestamp="2006-06-23 04:36:00.0">Troublemaker:The concept that matter is made up out of &amp;#8216;atoms&amp;#8217; is almost 2500 years old. Basically the greeks thought up the idea of atoms, and even guessed that there was a huge vacuum inside them. On the other hand, what they thought atoms were bares very little resemblence to reality. There is a fuller description of this here, or just google it.</comment>
    <comment id="10" author="Science" timestamp="2006-06-23 05:20:00.0">Joe, read points #2 and #3 on the link you have given: the Greeks did not predict a vacuum inside atoms.  They falsely predicted atoms are unsplittable (this prediction is so strong that the very word atom means &amp;#8220;It then follows that there can be no void inside an atom itself. Otherwise an atom would be subject to changes from outside and could disintegrate. Then, it would not be an atom. &amp;#8220;We know this is incorrect. In 1911, Ernest Rutherford discovered the nucleus, demonstrating in the process that a single atom is mostly empty space.&amp;#8221; The first person to publish the prediction that INSIDE atoms (not beetween different atoms!) there is a void was George Louis LeSage (click my name for details) in his essay &amp;#8216;Newtonian Lucretius&amp;#8217;, New Memoirs of the Royal Academy, 1782 (Berlin: Decker, 1784), pp. 404-32. He had a hard time from his peers, the paper begins with the quotation: &amp;#226;&amp;#8364;&amp;#732;In any matter, the first systems make people excessively conclusive, closed, cautions of others. And does it not seem that this truth is the price of some hardening of reason?&amp;#226;&amp;#8364;&amp;#8482; &amp;#226;&amp;#8364;&amp;#8220; Fontenelle, in the eulogy of Cassini.</comment>
    <comment id="11" author="Joe" timestamp="2006-06-23 05:28:00.0">Science, I thought I made it clear that what the Greeks believed does not correspond to how we now know atoms to behave. I am not saying that anything about their theory was completely correct. I was merely pointing out to Troublemaker that the concept of atoms existed at the time of Copernicus, and that most of matter was predicted to be empty space. Ok, I shouldn&amp;#8217;t have said &amp;#8220;vacuum inside them&amp;#8221;, my bad! I was refering to the Greeks prediction that atoms occupied a small fraction of space within matter. My point was only that the necessary ideas already existed for Copernicus to be able to make the analogy.</comment>
    <comment id="12" author="Science" timestamp="2006-06-23 05:37:00.0">&lt;blockquote&gt; I was refering to the Greeks prediction that atoms occupied a small fraction of space within matter. &amp;#8230; My point was only that the necessary ideas already existed for Copernicus to be able to make the analogy.  &lt;blockquote&gt; But I&amp;#8217;ve just explained the atomic idea came about in 1784, not in Greek times.  If you have two atoms a distance apart, Greeks said there is vacuum between them.  This has nothing to do with void inside atoms. Copernicus actually built on the work of Aristarchus of Samos, who had a solar system model.  Aristarchus was suppressed because everyone else ignored him.  Copernicus was taken more seriously because he fiddled a system with circular (not elliptical) orbits and twice as many epicycles as Ptolemy&amp;#8217;s earth-centred universe system, to fit the data.  The correct model emerged emerged a century after Copernicus when Kepler discovered elliptical orbits were correct.</comment>
    <comment id="13" author="Troublemaker" timestamp="2006-06-23 17:32:00.0">Science has largely made my point for me, but let me clarify: the original statement was that the enormity of the empty space inside the atom somehow inspired Copernicus, and this is blatantly false.  That&amp;#8217;s all I was trying to say.  Yes, the idea that matter is made up of tiny little units is very old, but the idea that these units are mostly vacuous space is not.</comment>
    <comment id="14" author="Pingback  from mis 3 quarks &amp;#187; Blog Archive &amp;#187; El &amp;#195;&amp;#161;tomo de hidr&amp;#195;&amp;#179;geno en perspectiva" timestamp="2006-06-26 22:20:00.0">[&amp;#8230;] Ya en la noche, le&amp;#195;&amp;#173; esta nota en Cosmic Variance y entend&amp;#195;&amp;#173; por qu&amp;#195;&amp;#169; no hab&amp;#195;&amp;#173;a quedado del todo contento con el &amp;#195;&amp;#161;tomo de hidr&amp;#195;&amp;#179;geno. [&amp;#8230;]</comment>
  </comment-list>
</page>

