<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <post author="JoAnne" timestamp="0002-11-30 00:00:00.0">
    <title>End of the summer school season</title>
    <sentence-list count="26">
      <sentence position="1" labelers="1, 2, 4">Hey, Lufthansa has wireless in the sky how cool is that!</sentence>
      <sentence position="2" labelers="2, 4">So here I am at roughly 38,000 ft, somewhere over Canada, 6.5 hours into the flight with 4.5 hours left to go .</sentence>
      <sentence position="3" labelers="1, 2, 3, 4">I m on my way home from the International Center for Theoretical Physics (ICTP) in Trieste, Italy, where one of the last summer schools of the season just finished.</sentence>
      <sentence position="4" labelers="1, 3, 4">The topic was Expecting LHC, which was the hot topic for summer schools this year.</sentence>
      <sentence position="5" labelers="4">In fact, everybody who is anybody had one.</sentence>
      <sentence position="6">The LHC is turning on next year and everyone wants the new crop of graduate students to be prepared!</sentence>
      <sentence position="7" labelers="1">The school was great and I enjoyed the whole experience.</sentence>
      <sentence position="8">(But, then again, I adore Italy!)</sentence>
      <sentence position="9">My lectures were on Non-Supersymmetric Physics Beyond the Standard Model and Extra Dimensions.</sentence>
      <sentence position="10">That s both a fairly broad and specific topic!</sentence>
      <sentence position="11" labelers="3">I first reviewed the symmetries of the Standard Model, which any model of new physics must clearly satisfy, and briefly covered something called Little Higgs models as they contain new quarks, new gauge bosons, and new Higgs bosons, all at once!</sentence>
      <sentence position="12" labelers="3">However, I spent most of my lectures on Extra Dimensions, covering the motivation, basic theory, and collider signatures for the main models.</sentence>
      <sentence position="13" labelers="1">Other lecturers covered the Standard Model (QCD and Electroweak and Heavy Flavors), Higgs, Supersymmetry, and the LHC accelerator and detectors.</sentence>
      <sentence position="14">The students were great!</sentence>
      <sentence position="15">It is always a joy to lecture to a room full of enthusiastic students.</sentence>
      <sentence position="16">They were chock full of good questions and were not shy about asking them, so the lectures (and the coffee breaks, and the meals) were very interactive.</sentence>
      <sentence position="17" labelers="4">There were about 100 students registered from various places ranging from Pakistan to Palestine.</sentence>
      <sentence position="18">This set of kids shows that the world is full of eager, bright and budding physicists!</sentence>
      <sentence position="19" labelers="1, 2, 3">The main program of the ICTP is to foster the development of theoretical physicists from developing countries.</sentence>
      <sentence position="20">The Center was founded in 1964 by Abdus Salam, a theorist from Pakistan who was a co-creator of the Standard Model, and it serves its purpose very well.</sentence>
      <sentence position="21">There are many shining examples of successful theorists who have worked there, including Gia Dvali who co-invented the model of Large Extra Dimensions (a main feature of my lectures) while he was there.</sentence>
      <sentence position="22" labelers="1, 2">Us lecturers were very well looked after, pretty much as described by Sean when he lectured at their Cosmology school earlier this year.</sentence>
      <sentence position="23" labelers="2, 3, 4">Since he already posted a picture of the guesthouse, I will share a picture of the jellyfish with you instead.</sentence>
      <sentence position="24">(Be thankful you are spared my numerous sunset shots.)</sentence>
      <sentence position="25" labelers="2, 3, 4">The small bay of the Adriatic Sea where the ICTP and its Guesthouse sits was filled with the things, about 1-2 ft long.</sentence>
      <sentence position="26" labelers="2">Superb!</sentence>
    </sentence-list>
  </post>
  <comment-list count="22">
    <comment id="1" author="graviton383" timestamp="2006-09-18 17:26:00.0">They look like they&amp;#8217;re jellyfish..</comment>
    <comment id="2" author="Quasar9" timestamp="2006-09-18 18:13:00.0">Hi JoAnne,jellyfish? but are they in the Adriatic?are they in the pool, or is the pool IN the Adriatic?I don&amp;#8217;t know about the rest of the cv visitors, but sunsets are my favourite pics and time of day!Glad students from all over including Pakistan &amp;amp; Palestine are getting the opportunity to participate in exciting research looking at  a future. 38,000 feet eh! Go Lufthansa Go.Does that mean you&amp;#8217;ve just joined the Mile high clubYou know those who go wireless &amp;amp; do it 12 kms up in da clouds&amp;#8212;</comment>
    <comment id="3" author="Dimitri Terryn" timestamp="2006-09-18 18:23:00.0">&amp;#8220;Hey, Lufthansa has wireless in the sky &amp;#226;&amp;#8364;&amp;#8220; how cool is that!&amp;#8221; Hurray for European carriers! What kind of plane was it?</comment>
    <comment id="4" author="Babe in the Universe" timestamp="2006-09-18 19:51:00.0">If you took Lufthansa, I am guessing a 747-400 and Boeing&amp;#8217;s wireless system.  You will be sorry to hear that Boeing is cancelling this system for lack of customers. Have you seen animations of the 747-8 on Boeing.com?  It may even have a bar, something planes have needed for a long time.  It will kick Airbus&amp;#8217; behind.</comment>
    <comment id="5" author="Rajesh Raut" timestamp="2006-09-18 19:57:00.0">No new quarks!</comment>
    <comment id="6" author="Jack" timestamp="2006-09-18 20:00:00.0">During a brief visit to a small town near Trieste I enjoyed the headlines in the local newspaper; the Triestine sense of what constitutes &amp;#8220;news&amp;#8221; seems to be a little idiosyncratic. On my first day there the town was placarded with signs announcing &amp;#8220;JELLYFISH INVADE THE GULF&amp;#8221; [of Trieste, that is&amp;#8230;]. A few days later the big news was &amp;#8220;ELEVEN ANCIENTS FOUND DRUNK ON HIGH FLOOR OF BUILDING&amp;#8221;.</comment>
    <comment id="7" author="L" timestamp="2006-09-18 21:13:00.0">love the jellyfish shot</comment>
    <comment id="8" author="Q" timestamp="2006-09-19 02:47:00.0">Well wireless from 38,000 feetI guess with the &amp;#8216;mushrooming&amp;#8217; size of the collider budgetthey could put you in space next, along with that other dual (or is it triple) nationality heavenly body&amp;#8212;</comment>
    <comment id="9" author="Dimitri Terryn" timestamp="2006-09-19 03:39:00.0">&amp;#8220;Have you seen animations of the 747-8 on Boeing.com? It may even have a bar, something planes have needed for a long time. It will kick Airbus&amp;#226;&amp;#8364;&amp;#8482; behind.&amp;#8221; You are aware that there is something like the A380 aren&amp;#8217;t you? From wikipedia : &amp;#8220;Initial publicity stressed the comfort and space of the A380&amp;#8217;s cabin, which offers room for such installations as relaxation areas, bars, duty-free shops, and beauty salons. One A380 customer likely to use innovative amenities is Virgin Atlantic Airways, which has a bar in Business Class on its aircraft, and has announced plans to include casinos, double beds, a gymnasium and showers on its A380s.&amp;#8221; So the the 747-800 may even have a bar? Jolly good!</comment>
    <comment id="10" author="Robert" timestamp="2006-09-19 04:11:00.0">Great pic. Brings back memories of a school I attended at ICTP to which I took my scuba gear and did a spectacular night dive right below the institute at the Adriatico hotel.</comment>
    <comment id="11" author="Quasar9" timestamp="2006-09-19 04:30:00.0">Hi Dimitri, don&amp;#8217;t take the bait!No need to start a trans-atlantic &amp;#8216;political&amp;#8217; incident. We know the A380 and Airbus are at the cutting edge of commercial passenger travel and comfort.The Old mother continent is the birth place and historical stronghold of past &amp;amp; future innovation, even if we are a little short of landmarks for space launch pads.Personally, I prefer Ocean cruise liners and real luxury travel, much more leg room, and disco dancing at nights, and anyway what&amp;#8217;s the rush. If I&amp;#8217;m really in a hurry just use a military jetfighter.And if I don&amp;#8217;t wanna have to physically (bodily) travel use video-conferencing. Be environmental save on airmiles and jet fuel CO2 emissions, and all those boring stop-overs at hubs and check-ins at airports.&amp;#8211;</comment>
    <comment id="12" author="collin" timestamp="2006-09-19 11:05:00.0">Trieste, eh? Any good wines from Friuli or the Veneto?</comment>
    <comment id="13" author="pakistan" timestamp="2006-09-20 00:55:00.0">What are the crucial differences between a Croation and a Bulgarian accents?</comment>
    <comment id="14" author="mark" timestamp="2006-09-19 13:16:00.0">must say, the jellyfish picture is beautiful</comment>
    <comment id="15" author="puzzled" timestamp="2006-09-20 14:01:00.0">Pakistan: What are the crucial differences between a Croation and a Bulgarian accents? The only differences are in grammar, vocabulary and pronunciation. Also Bulgarian and Croation are not mutually comperensible. Other than that they are almost carbon copies.</comment>
    <comment id="16" author="AstroCook" timestamp="2006-09-20 18:57:00.0">I recently heard that the LHC is requiring participating researchers to BUY TIME on it for their research&amp;#8230;  is this true?  I hear the price is extremely high! And why!?   We shared our collider, why can&amp;#8217;t they?  What is the reason for the buy-in?</comment>
    <comment id="17" author="JoAnne" timestamp="2006-09-20 19:56:00.0">AstroCook:  No, not true!  You got a hold of a false rumor there. Collin:  Had two great local wines in Trieste.  Couldn&amp;#8217;t tell you what the red wine was, but it tasted similar to an American Zinfandel.  The white was something they used to call &amp;#8220;Tokay&amp;#8221; (don&amp;#8217;t know the grape) but had to change the name  to avoid confusion with the Hungarian Tokay.  Also had a spectacular (and expensive) Amarone. All:  The jellyfish were definitely IN the Adriatic itself in very large numbers.</comment>
    <comment id="18" author="Pingback  from The Square Root of 98 | Cosmic Variance" timestamp="2006-09-20 23:30:00.0">[&amp;#8230;] I bet you all are not aware, but there is a new test of nationality being performed when one enters the US. I arrived in the San Francisco airport on Monday night, passed passport control, picked up my luggage, and went to hand in my customs form, which is the last step in the arrivals process. The customs agent stopped me dead in my tracks. He first asked, &amp;#226;&amp;#8364;&amp;#339;Are you an American.&amp;#226;&amp;#8364;&amp;#65533; Obviously I answered &amp;#226;&amp;#8364;&amp;#339;yes&amp;#226;&amp;#8364;&amp;#65533; straight-away. Then he asked, &amp;#226;&amp;#8364;&amp;#339;OK, then, what is the square root of 98?&amp;#226;&amp;#8364;&amp;#65533; [&amp;#8230;]</comment>
    <comment id="19" author="Amara" timestamp="2006-09-24 06:04:00.0">The jellyfish have been a problem this summer all through the Mediterranean. That Internet service should be phased out soon. Myself, I don&amp;#8217;t understand why Boeing cancelled their Internet service. It seemed very popular on the Lufthansa FRA-LAX flight I was on last winter. So popular, that there wasn&amp;#8217;t enough bandwidth to accomodate all of the people who wanted to use it. For example, &amp;#8216;Peak times&amp;#8217; existed, so that the best time to get on the Internet were during the meal service. European airlines, with this Internet service failure, are now looking forward to offering mobile use in the sky. As someone who tries hard to get a good sleep on flights, this is not an attractive thought.</comment>
    <comment id="20" author="Quasar9" timestamp="2006-09-25 02:47:00.0">Hi JoAnne, I know there are jelly fish in the Adriatic.I meant your photo, is that a pool in the adriatic, a man made pool, or steps leading into the actual sea&amp;#8212;</comment>
    <comment id="21" author="Quasar9" timestamp="2006-09-25 02:51:00.0">Perhaps it is just a trick of the lightbut it looks like a straight ledge on the rightA step perhaps?And the bottom looks like the bottom of a poolnot some rocky or sandy beach/shore.But my eyesight has been known to deceive meand it is a beautiful pic of beautiful jellyfish.&amp;#8212;</comment>
    <comment id="22" author="JoAnne" timestamp="2006-09-25 13:27:00.0">Quasar9:  The photo is of the Adriatic alright.  I was standing on a jetty which protects a marina near the ICTP guest house.</comment>
  </comment-list>
</page>

