<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <post author="Sean" timestamp="2005-11-28 13:00:00.0">
    <title>Titling</title>
    <sentence-list count="40">
      <sentence position="1" labelers="1, 2, 3, 4">For reasons having nothing to do with the obscure films post, I recently had the opportunity to see Terry Gilliam s Brazil (for perhaps the fifth or sixth time).</sentence>
      <sentence position="2" labelers="1, 2, 3, 4">It s a close call between that and Casablanca for my all-time favorite movie how can you go wrong combining Kafka and Orwell with Monty Python and Tom Stoppard?</sentence>
      <sentence position="3">(Brazil, I mean, not Casablanca.)</sentence>
      <sentence position="4" labelers="1, 2, 3">Of course there is a wonderful backstory to the making of the movie, in which Universal studios chopped up the movie to make a love conquers all version with a happy ending, which Gilliam refused to have his name associated with.</sentence>
      <sentence position="5" labelers="1, 2, 3">Fortunately that version never got released, as Gilliam resorted (intentionally or not) to a fiendishly clever strategy: he surreptitiously showed his version to groups of film critics, and the LA film critics society awarded its best picture of the year award to a movie that hadn t even been released.</sentence>
      <sentence position="6" labelers="1, 2, 3">The awards, which Universal would much have preferred go to its other movie Out of Africa, embarassed the studio into letting Gilliam s version be distributed, albeit without any support.</sentence>
      <sentence position="7" labelers="1">You can read all sorts of fun trivia in the Brazil FAQ.</sentence>
      <sentence position="8" labelers="3, 4">My favorite is this: Sidney Scheinberg, president of Universal and the man in charge of the happy-ending version, decided he didn t like the title, and solicited suggestions from his staff.</sentence>
      <sentence position="9" labelers="3, 4">(To be fair, the title would have made less for his version; in Gilliam s version there is an elaborate soundtrack by Michael Kamen that is constructed primarily out of variations of the song Brazil, all of which was replaced in Scheinberg s version by rock music, to attract teenagers.)</sentence>
      <sentence position="10" labelers="1">Here are the suggested replacement titles: If Osmosis, Who Are You?Some Day SoonVortex Day Dreams and Night TripperWhat a Future!</sentence>
      <sentence position="11">Litterbugs</sentence>
      <sentence position="12">The Works</sentence>
      <sentence position="13">Skylight City</sentence>
      <sentence position="14">You Show Me Your Dream Access</sentence>
      <sentence position="15">Arresting Developments</sentence>
      <sentence position="16">Nude Descending Bathroom Scale</sentence>
      <sentence position="17">Lords of the Files</sentence>
      <sentence position="18">Dreamscape</sentence>
      <sentence position="19">The Staplegunners Progress</sentence>
      <sentence position="20">Forever More</sentence>
      <sentence position="21">The Right to Bear Arms</sentence>
      <sentence position="22">Explanada Fortunata Is Not My Real Name</sentence>
      <sentence position="23">All Too Soon</sentence>
      <sentence position="24">Chaos</sentence>
      <sentence position="25">Where Were We?</sentence>
      <sentence position="26">Disconnected Parties</sentence>
      <sentence position="27">Blank/Blank</sentence>
      <sentence position="28">Erotic</sentence>
      <sentence position="29">Shadow Time</sentence>
      <sentence position="30">Maelstrom Forces of Darkness</sentence>
      <sentence position="31">The Man in the Custom Tailored T-shirt</sentence>
      <sentence position="32">Fold, Spindle, MutilateCan t Anybody Here Play the Cymbals?</sentence>
      <sentence position="33">Sign on High</sentence>
      <sentence position="34">The Ball Bearing Electro Memory Circuit Buster</sentence>
      <sentence position="35">This Escalator Doesn t Stop At Your Station</sentence>
      <sentence position="36">Gnu Yak, Gnu Yak, and Other Bestial Places</sentence>
      <sentence position="37">I can t for the life of me understand what they were thinking for most of these.</sentence>
      <sentence position="38">(Okay, I kind of like Litterbugs.)</sentence>
      <sentence position="39">I suspect they had a thought process along the lines of Well, the movie s kind of weird, so let s make the title weird!</sentence>
      <sentence position="40">I ve had my own battles with Physical Review over titles of my papers, but nothing like this.</sentence>
    </sentence-list>
  </post>
  <comment-list count="15">
    <comment id="1" author="Amara" timestamp="2005-11-28 13:12:00.0">I recently picked up a DVD of this film (also a favorite of mine) with Italian subtitles for that extra touch of bizarreness. You mentioned Kafka, did you mean the film? I think a perfect movie evening would be to play Brazil and Kafka back-to-back.Kafka: http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0102181/</comment>
    <comment id="2" author="Clifford" timestamp="2005-11-28 14:18:00.0">I don&amp;#8217;t have an all time favourite movie to mention -there are just too many candidates-  but Brazil is high on the list, and maybe near Dr Strangelove&amp;#8230;the full title of which is also excellent: Dr. Strangelove or: How I Learned to Stop Worrying and Love the Bomb I wonder what the boardroom arguments were about that title?! And of course, I borrowed from this title for my first ever blog post. -cvj</comment>
    <comment id="3" author="RPM" timestamp="2005-11-28 14:33:00.0">I always wondered about the title of the film.  Has Gilliam ever made a movie that was completed without going rediculously over budget and released to his liking?  If you&amp;#8217;re a Gilliam fan, you really have to see Lost in La Mancha &amp;#8212; a documentary of Gilliam trying to make a Don Quixote film that really captures the absurdity of Terry Gilliam&amp;#8217;s film making.</comment>
    <comment id="4" author="Amara" timestamp="2005-11-28 15:06:00.0">Oooh&amp;#8230;Dr. Strangelove, another favorite! Did you know that Kubrick filmed a full scene of a War Room pie fight,  that was later cut from the final movie? I wish it would have made it in. Here are some cut views of the pie fight scene. http://www.geocities.com/SunsetStrip/Underground/9798/piefight.htm Truth is stranger than fiction, however, because Dr. Strangelove is almost a documentary. http://www.politicalnovel.org/drstrangelove.html &amp;#8220;One essential point should emerge from all the hoopla: &amp;#8220;Strangelove&amp;#8221; is far more than a satire. In its own loopy way, the movie is a remarkably fact-based and specific guide to some of the oddest, most secretive chapters of the cold war.&amp;#8221;</comment>
    <comment id="5" author="Tim D" timestamp="2005-11-28 15:09:00.0">Yeah, &amp;#8220;Brazil&amp;#8221; is definitely in my top 5 (if I *had* to pick right now I&amp;#8217;d say Spirited Away, Matewan, The Crying Game and Rushmore, I think) In my mind, Brazil is linked with &amp;#8220;Blade Runner&amp;#8221;, another excellent film with some studio funny business regarding the ending.</comment>
    <comment id="6" author="Kea" timestamp="2005-11-28 15:10:00.0">Brazil, yes! Definitely one of my favourites. I&amp;#8217;m quite fond of other Gilliam films, too, such as the Monkeys one&amp;#8230;what&amp;#8217;s it called?</comment>
    <comment id="7" author="dswift" timestamp="2005-11-28 15:52:00.0">Ah. One who sees the light. It took me about 10 laps through Brazil before I finally stitched the whole thing together, at which point I declared Brazil the greatest movie ever made. I admit that this grandiose pronoucement is irrelevant.  Brazil is not a movie for movie buffs. Roger Ebert, for example, thinks Roadhouse is a better movie than Brazil. What&amp;#8217;s relevant is the fact that Brazil one of the great artworks of 20th century. I am prepared to argue this ad nauseam upon request. To fellow Brazil fans who lurk, may I direct you to a moment of genius I bet few have taken in full?  It&amp;#8217;s the party scene when Sam is having an awkward chat with Shirley on a couch. He leaves her clumsily and apologizes. Wittin the space of about 1.5 seconds, Shirley delivers a mad assortment of expressions &amp;#8212; pity, disgust, shame, forgiveness, et al. It&amp;#8217;s an astonishing bit that demands frame-by-frame examination.</comment>
    <comment id="8" author="Sean" timestamp="2005-11-28 15:54:00.0">dswift&amp;#8211;yes, I noticed precisely that scene.  Fantastic.</comment>
    <comment id="9" author="Cygnus" timestamp="2005-11-28 15:55:00.0">Kea: That&amp;#8217;s Twelve Monkeys, you&amp;#8217;re talking about I think. Brazil, is an awesome movie. Having sort of missed the obscure movies thread I&amp;#8217;d like to mention that if you liked Brazil, you might also like Delicatessen.  Though, in my opinion, Dr Stranglove beats all of these pretty comfortably for the top English film slot. And talking about science, anyone here seen October Sky?</comment>
    <comment id="10" author="David" timestamp="2005-11-28 16:43:00.0">Amazing&amp;#8230;I saw Brazil many years ago and still think of it as the best film I ever saw. The memory of what happened in it is fading now, just remember being greatly impressed at the time and the one scene where the buildings start shooting up into the sky. It sure is surprising to see that quite a few others here also think this, since, e.g. the people I saw it with thought it was good but not fantastic, and most others I&amp;#8217;ve mentioned it to since then hadn&amp;#8217;t even heard of it (thought I was talking about &amp;#8220;Boys from Brazil&amp;#8221;). I wonder if there&amp;#8217;s a natural inclination for physicists to like this film&amp;#8230;</comment>
    <comment id="11" author="Kea" timestamp="2005-11-28 16:48:00.0">Twelve Monkeys, yes, thanks.  Not up there with Brazil but pretty darned good.For comparable brilliance, how about Mulholland Drive?</comment>
    <comment id="12" author="Thomas Palm" timestamp="2005-11-29 04:57:00.0">Have you considered that some of those silly names may have been hints from the staff to leave the original title intact? In some places you don&amp;#8217;t openly tell the boss that he is wrong.</comment>
    <comment id="13" author="schnitzi" timestamp="2005-11-29 07:29:00.0">I watched Brazil on TV a few years ago, and guess what?  They had chopped off the very last scene, where the doctors faces lean into view, and you realize&amp;#8230;  They were apparently quite intent on making it a happy ending, in at least one forum they could control.  Bastards.</comment>
    <comment id="14" author="colhawk" timestamp="2005-12-02 14:50:00.0">Another physics person who likes Brazil a lot.. First time I saw it I had to leave just before the end,  but I was uneasy about the seeming happy ending.. I felt much better when I watched the whole thing later!  I guess you could say our hero achieved some kind of nirvana in which he was beyond harm. Incidentally Kate Bush sang an interesting version of Brazil, no doubt in connection with her pal Terry. She just brought out a new album after a 12 odd years break.</comment>
    <comment id="15" author="Amara" timestamp="2005-12-02 16:49:00.0">Thanks for the heads up colhawk! I thought she&amp;#8217;d left the business for good. I&amp;#8217;ve missed her music! Did you see that she has a song called pi? http://www.katebush.com/katebush_html/lyrics.html &amp;#207;&amp;#8364; Sweet and gentle and sensitive manWith an obsessive nature and deep fascinationFor numbersAnd a complete infatuation with the calculationOf PI Oh he love, he love, he loveHe does love his numbersAnd they run, they run, they run himIn a great big circleIn a circle of infinity 3.1415926535 8979323846 264 338 3279 Oh he does, he does, he doesHe does love his numbersAnd they run, they run, they run himIn a great big circleIn a circle of infinityBut he must, he must, he mustPut a number to it 50288419 716939937510582319749 44 592307816406286208 821 4808651 32 Oh he love, he love, he loveHe does love his numbersAnd they run, they run, they run himIn a great big circleIn a circle of infinity 82306647 0938446095 505 8223&amp;#8230;</comment>
  </comment-list>
</page>

