<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <post author="Sean" timestamp="0002-11-30 00:00:00.0">
    <title>arxiv Find:  Cycling in the Throat</title>
    <sentence-list count="23">
      <sentence position="1" labelers="1, 3">One of the reasons we (or I, anyway) don t do more science posts is that it s hard to do a good job.</sentence>
      <sentence position="2" labelers="1, 3">Cutting and pasting and linking is easy, whereas it takes time to really absorb some interesting scientific concept and present it in a hopefully-understandable way.</sentence>
      <sentence position="3">And we re all amateur blogging hobbyists with day jobs.</sentence>
      <sentence position="4" labelers="1, 3, 4">But I had the idea that it might be fun to get glimpses at what is going on in the field by taking occasional amusing papers that appear on arxiv.org, and just reposting their abstracts here with a couple of words.</sentence>
      <sentence position="5">If anyone doesn t follow the details, that s okay; think of it as performance art, and the abstracts as little prose poems.</sentence>
      <sentence position="6" labelers="1, 4">Today s arxiv find is hep-th/0701252, Cycling in the Throat by Easson, Gregory, Tasinato and Zavala.</sentence>
      <sentence position="7">Here s the abstract:</sentence>
      <sentence position="8" labelers="2, 4">We analyse the dynamics of a probe D3-(anti-)brane propagating in a warped string compactification, making use of the Dirac-Born-Infeld action approximation.</sentence>
      <sentence position="9" labelers="2, 4">We also examine the time dependent expansion of such moving branes from the mirage cosmology perspective, where cosmology is induced by the brane motion in the background spacetime.</sentence>
      <sentence position="10" labelers="2">A range of physically interesting backgrounds are considered: AdS5, Klebanov-Tseytlin and Klebanov-Strassler.</sentence>
      <sentence position="11" labelers="2, 3">Our focus is on exploring what new phenomenology is obtained from giving the brane angular momentum in the extra dimensions.</sentence>
      <sentence position="12" labelers="2, 3, 4">We find that in general, angular momentum creates a centrifugal barrier, causing bouncing cosmologies.</sentence>
      <sentence position="13" labelers="2, 3">More unexpected, and more interesting, is the existence of bound orbits, corresponding to cyclic universes.</sentence>
      <sentence position="14">See?</sentence>
      <sentence position="15">Poetry.</sentence>
      <sentence position="16" labelers="1, 2, 4">The basic idea here is to explore what can happen when a 3-brane (which could be our visible universe, if all of the particles of the Standard Model were confined to it) doesn t just sit there in the extra dimensions, but zooms and twirls around like a multidimensional figure skater.</sentence>
      <sentence position="17" labelers="1, 4">Ever since Randall and Sundrum caught on to the fun things that can happen when extra dimensions are warped, we continue to discover new and interesting scenarios for these hypothetical directions of space.</sentence>
      <sentence position="18" labelers="3">This paper sets the branes to spinning, and steps back to look at the results, which apparently include bouncing cosmologies.</sentence>
      <sentence position="19" labelers="1">I might worry about stability in the presence of perturbations, but that s just something to do for a follow-up paper we ll never run out of good questions to ask.</sentence>
      <sentence position="20">Some other fun papers this week: Jackiw and Pi, Chiral Gauge Theory for Graphene, cond-mat/0701760.</sentence>
      <sentence position="21">Bekenstein, The modified Newtonian dynamics-MOND-and its implications for new physics, astro-ph/0701848.</sentence>
      <sentence position="22">Bojowald, Quantum gravity and cosmological observations, gr-qc/0701142.</sentence>
      <sentence position="23">Brandenberger, String Gas Cosmology and Structure Formation - A Brief Review, hep-th/0702001.</sentence>
    </sentence-list>
  </post>
  <comment-list count="19">
    <comment id="1" author="Matt" timestamp="2007-02-03 14:26:00.0">One abstract I found amusing on arxiv last year was this. I was just relieved to know that &amp;#8220;&amp;#8230;we are highly unlikely to be vacuum fluctuations&amp;#8230;&amp;#8221;</comment>
    <comment id="2" author="BG" timestamp="2007-02-03 15:02:00.0">I think my favorite paper ever in terms of sheer poetry of the title and abstract is gr-qc/9707027 The phrase &amp;#8220;arbitrarily short hair&amp;#8221; gets me every time.</comment>
    <comment id="3" author="Mr Knightley" timestamp="2007-02-03 15:10:00.0">The king of titles: http://arxiv.org/abs/hep-th/0411268</comment>
    <comment id="4" author="JoAnne" timestamp="2007-02-03 15:23:00.0">In the you know you&amp;#8217;re in trouble when category, not only did I understand the abstract, but the paper sounds darned interesting!  I never thought about giving branes angular momentum in the extra dimensions. Hmmmm&amp;#8230;one could do stuff with that.  In fact, I think I can calculate a collider signature for that.  Thanks for pointing this out Sean - you&amp;#8217;ve seriously given me a new idea to tinker with!</comment>
    <comment id="5" author="Uncle Enzo" timestamp="2007-02-03 17:20:00.0">So&amp;#8230;.uhhh&amp;#8230;how would you calculate that?  Step by step.  I&amp;#8217;m not going to do it, don&amp;#8217;t worry.  I&amp;#8217;m just curious, that&amp;#8217;s all.</comment>
    <comment id="6" author="Antti" timestamp="2007-02-03 21:43:00.0">As far as titles go, hep-th/0107199 is my all time favorite in the &amp;#8220;funny titles&amp;#8221; category (though perhaps that tells more about me than about the title&amp;#8230;)</comment>
    <comment id="7" author="Mark" timestamp="2007-02-03 22:06:00.0">I think I should avoid commenting on this, since Easson was my postdoc, but I think posting about a particularly interesting arxiv posting is a very good idea.</comment>
    <comment id="8" author="Pingback  from Not Even Wrong &amp;#187; Blog Archive &amp;#187; Odds and Ends" timestamp="2007-02-04 12:18:00.0">[&amp;#8230;] Sean Carroll seems to find it amusing that many articles on the arXiv can now be thought of as a new form of performance art. John Horgan, who got a lot of grief years ago for accusing physicists of engaging in &amp;#8220;ironic science&amp;#8221;, should really enjoy this. [&amp;#8230;]</comment>
    <comment id="9" author="JoAnne" timestamp="2007-02-04 01:15:00.0">Uncle Enzo:  You&amp;#8217;ll be the first to know when the paper comes out!  Seriously, we live in a competitive climate and I can&amp;#8217;t divulge my calculation ideas until it&amp;#8217;s finished (if/when).  But, I am excited about the idea and never dreamed research ideas would propagate from a blog!</comment>
    <comment id="10" author="Amara" timestamp="2007-02-04 04:39:00.0">Here&amp;#8217;s one of my favorites(?): Astrophysics, abstractastro-ph/0005546 From: Vladimir A. LefebvreDate: Sat, 27 May 2000 01:51:28 GMT   (15kb) Cosmic Intelligence and Black Holes Authors: Vladimir A. Lefebvre, Yuri N. EfremovComments: 13 pages, accepted for publication at Zemlia i Vselennaya (Earthand Universe) for No.4, 2000Journal-ref: Zemlya i Vselennaya (Earth and the Universe), 5 (2000) 69-83 The paper is devoted to a new direction in SETI. After a general discussion of the field, the authors put forth the hypothesis that the black holes may serve as a physical substratum for intelligent beings. This hypothesis is based on four parallels between the brain-psyche system, on the one hand, and black holes, on the other. (1) The descriptions of brain and psyche, in the system brain-psyche, are complementary to each other, as descriptions by internal and external observers of a black hole in Susskind-t&amp;#8217;Hooft&amp;#8217;s schema. (2) There is an aspect of the inner structure of a black hole in Kerr&amp;#8217;s model of the rotating black hole that is isomorphic to the structure of the human subjective domain in the psychological model of reflexion. (3) Both black holes and the brain-psyche system have a facet which can be represented using thermodynamic concepts. (4) The brain lends itself to a holographic description; as has been recently demonstrated by Susskind, black holes can also be described holographically. The authors speculate that the intelligent black holes can generate other black holes by triggering creation of massive stars from which new black holes arise after the stars&amp;#8217; collapse. In addition, the authors analyze certain strange phenomena related to the birth of young massive stars which may or may not be connected with such a triggering.</comment>
    <comment id="11" author="Arun" timestamp="2007-02-04 08:53:00.0">Skating away on the thin ice of &amp;#8230;.</comment>
    <comment id="12" author="Amara" timestamp="2007-02-04 11:12:00.0">&amp;#8230; a cold, icy, bottomless, viscous mass, where my brain ceases to exist in the form known as &amp;#8220;I&amp;#8221;. Yes, Arun, that&amp;#8217;s what some of these ArXiV abstracts do to my mind.</comment>
    <comment id="13" author="Walt" timestamp="2007-02-04 11:35:00.0">There&amp;#8217;s a statistics paper entitled &amp;#8220;The Earth is round (p</comment>
    <comment id="14" author="Gem" timestamp="2007-02-05 08:03:00.0">As far as &amp;#8220;holy&amp;#8221; titles go, I&amp;#8217;d say this is the best: http://arxiv.org/abs/hep-th/9610135</comment>
    <comment id="15" author="B" timestamp="2007-02-05 09:28:00.0">See also: The Stupid Title List</comment>
    <comment id="16" author="Albert" timestamp="2007-02-05 19:28:00.0">decapitating tadpoles http://arxiv.org/abs/hep-th/0209226</comment>
    <comment id="17" author="citrine" timestamp="2007-02-06 18:11:00.0">I remember reading about the Cosmologist who wrote a pedantic sounding but meaningless paper using common technical terms in his field, and got it published in a Humanities research journal.</comment>
    <comment id="18" author="Haludza" timestamp="2007-02-08 20:47:00.0">&amp;#8216;Would Bohr be born if Bohm were born before Born?&amp;#8217;physics/0702069 Took me 5 minutes to get through that sentence!</comment>
    <comment id="19" author="Pingback  from Anomalous Presumptions &amp;#187; Metaphysics that matters" timestamp="2007-02-21 02:22:00.0">[&amp;#8230;] Esoteric questions in other disciplines always seem to be connected to issues that make sense to non-experts. The dynamics of a probe D3-(anti-)brane propagating in a warped string compactification bear on whether there&amp;#8217;s life after the big crunch. But technical problems in philosophy often seem disconnected from issues that matter to non-philosophers. [&amp;#8230;]</comment>
  </comment-list>
</page>

