<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <post author="Clifford" timestamp="2006-04-27 20:20:00.0">
    <title>Books Books Books!</title>
    <sentence-list count="24">
      <sentence position="1" labelers="1, 3, 4">In case you re in the area, please don t forget the Los Angeles Times Fesitval of Books this weekend, held over Saturday and Sunday at the UCLA campus.</sentence>
      <sentence position="2">It is a blast.</sentence>
      <sentence position="3" labelers="1, 3">There are book authors of various types and genres being celebrated as the celebrities they should be, with young girls and boys gasping and fainting as their idols go by.</sentence>
      <sentence position="4">Well, not quite, but I like to imagine this.</sentence>
      <sentence position="5">Here is the website with the schedule.</sentence>
      <sentence position="6">As they say there, you ll have:</sentence>
      <sentence position="7">131,000+ Passionate Readers370+ Famous Authors300+ Popular Exhibitors900+ Loyal Volunteers6 Exciting Stages2 Interactive Children s Areas</sentence>
      <sentence position="8" labelers="1, 3, 4">I went last year and can verify that it is a lot of fun.</sentence>
      <sentence position="9" labelers="1">Actually, this year I won t be able to see much because I promised to go with a big group to the top of Mount Wilson the fun way, which will take up most of Saturday.</sentence>
      <sentence position="10" labelers="3, 4">On Sunday, I m doing the church sermon thing I mentioned earlier and then they are taking me to lunch and doing more Q A, so I don t know when I ll make it over to UCLA that day.</sentence>
      <sentence position="11">I do get to go to one event for sure.</sentence>
      <sentence position="12" labelers="1, 2">My first LA Awards ceremony!!</sentence>
      <sentence position="13" labelers="2, 3">On Friday night I go to the LA Times Book Awards.</sentence>
      <sentence position="14" labelers="2">I won t be live blogging from it, as was done last year at The Elegant Variation.</sentence>
      <sentence position="15" labelers="2">I ll be too busy being embarrassed.</sentence>
      <sentence position="16" labelers="1, 2, 3, 4">You see, I looked at the list of nominees just now, and while several of the books are on my must get around to reading this gem list, such as (from the Science and Technology category) Chris Mooney s The Republican War on Science , and Sean B. Carroll s Endless Forms Most Beautiful: The New Science of Evo Devo and the Making of the Animal Kingdom , I have not read anything that has been nominated.</sentence>
      <sentence position="17" labelers="2">I ve just been too busy the last several months.</sentence>
      <sentence position="18" labelers="2">So it s going to be so embarrassing - I ll be exposed as a fraud!</sentence>
      <sentence position="19" labelers="1, 3">On the plus side, I ve been promised that I ll be introduced to lots of interesting authors, such as Mariana Gosnell, the author of Ice: The Nature, the History, and the Uses of an Astonishing Substance , which I suspect is a truly excellent book.</sentence>
      <sentence position="20" labelers="1">I m going to get in touch with my inner groupie, for all the right reasons (but remaining slightly aloof on the outside of course).</sentence>
      <sentence position="21" labelers="4">Hmmmm I wonder if I can speed-read a few of these overnight?</sentence>
      <sentence position="22" labelers="4">And whatever shall I wear do I finally get to wear that Tuxedo I bought a while back?</sentence>
      <sentence position="23" labelers="4">Is it too late to rent some expensive jewelry, or get a jeweller who wants the red carpet publicity to lend me some?</sentence>
      <sentence position="24">-cvj</sentence>
    </sentence-list>
  </post>
  <comment-list count="14">
    <comment id="1" author="Pyracantha" timestamp="2006-04-27 20:32:00.0">&amp;#8220;Our&amp;#8221; Sean Carroll writing on Evolution (or is it Devo are we not men?)? Or is there ANOTHER Sean Carroll prowling about writing science books?</comment>
    <comment id="2" author="Clifford" timestamp="2006-04-27 20:42:00.0">Yes. It is a biologist Carroll. Writes some really excelleent stuff. Check out Evo-Devo. It is not a new European dance craze, but a very interesting field of biology mixing developmental isues with evolutionary issues. I meant to do a post about it a while ago but never got around to it. -cvj</comment>
    <comment id="3" author="Moshe" timestamp="2006-04-27 20:53:00.0">Good luck with the cermon thing (noticed I did not say that before&amp;#8230;), the book awards seem oddly interesting- I&amp;#8217;m in the process of digesting the evo-devo book (by that other Sean Carroll), together with half of western civilization it seems, and so far so good. If you wish to speed read something from the list, how about the Murakami novel?  usually it is hard to put them down (this one if not bad, but some of his other novels are incredible).</comment>
    <comment id="4" author="Moshe" timestamp="2006-04-27 21:09:00.0">Sermon, I meant sermon (what is a cermon anyhow?), nevermind, good luck anyhow&amp;#8230;</comment>
    <comment id="5" author="Clifford" timestamp="2006-04-27 21:22:00.0">Thanks Moshe. Oh, a cermon is small, rare, inquisitive animal in the rodent family which is actually rather tasty roasted and sprinkled with rosemary. Bit more meat on them than gerbes, their stringier cousins. -cvj</comment>
    <comment id="6" author="Moshe" timestamp="2006-04-27 21:29:00.0">I knew it sounded familiar!  well, hopefully I will not come up with these exotic animals too frequently&amp;#8230;</comment>
    <comment id="7" author="Wowbagger" timestamp="2006-04-28 12:04:00.0">I know who&amp;#8217;s won the sci/tech prize, but I won&amp;#8217;t spoil the surprise for anyone&amp;#8230;</comment>
    <comment id="8" author="adam" timestamp="2006-04-28 07:55:00.0">Which reminds me that I have to go to the enormous &amp;#8216;Friends of the Library&amp;#8217; sale in our downtown, this weekend (first weekend was last weekend). I love me some books.</comment>
    <comment id="9" author="Christopehr Willard" timestamp="2006-04-28 10:45:00.0">Yeah, you could speed read them overnight &amp;#8212; Just like I speed-read War and Peace &amp;#8212; It&amp;#8217;s about Russia. (author of Garbage Head)</comment>
    <comment id="10" author="spyder" timestamp="2006-04-28 14:59:00.0">Another good reminder:  The LA Book Awards and LA Times Festival of Books is broadcast live on CSPAN, and replayed a number of times thereafter.  It is brilliant television, the science writing panels are very interesting and informative, and that doesn&amp;#8217;t begin to suggest how witty and wonderful they are.  So if you can&amp;#8217;t be at UCLA, then turn to CSPAN this weekend.</comment>
    <comment id="11" author="spyder" timestamp="2006-04-28 15:01:00.0">obviously my quick post above contains a glaring grammar error, for which i humbly beg forgiveness: &amp;#8220;are&amp;#8221; not &amp;#8220;is&amp;#8221; &amp;#8216;broadcast&amp;#8217; !</comment>
    <comment id="12" author="Clifford" timestamp="2006-04-28 16:07:00.0">televised!? Oh no&amp;#8230; Now I *do* have to wear that tux. -cvj</comment>
    <comment id="13" author="im" timestamp="2006-04-28 19:42:00.0">&amp;#8230;. and you definetely need some funky jewelry &amp;#8230;unfortunately I am not around, otherwise I would have been happy to lend you one of my special rings</comment>
    <comment id="14" author="Pingback  from I See Book People | Cosmic Variance" timestamp="2006-04-30 03:49:00.0">[&amp;#8230;] Well, I&amp;#8217;m recovering from an excellent hike up Mount Wilson with the USC Neurobiologists earlier today, so while I do that, I&amp;#8217;ll tell you about last night. Recall that the LA Times Book Festival is happening this weekend. [&amp;#8230;]</comment>
  </comment-list>
</page>

