<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <post author="" timestamp="2006-09-22 10:02:00.0">
    <title>More Add-Ons: NewsGator Desktop Sync (Beta)</title>
    <sentence-list count="11">
      <sentence position="1" labelers="1, 2, 3, 4">Add-ons for the IE platform are more than just toolbars, custom browsers and find-on-page add-ons.</sentence>
      <sentence position="2" labelers="2, 3">The edges of what you can do with the platform are virtually unlimited.</sentence>
      <sentence position="3" labelers="1, 2, 3, 4">Earlier this year at Mix06, Greg Reinacker and Walter VonKoch demo d a toolfor synchronizing the RSS platform state with your NewsGator online account.</sentence>
      <sentence position="4" labelers="1, 2, 3, 4">On Monday, Nick Harris (no relation) at NewsGator announcedthat the tool, renamed NewsGator Desktop Sync is available for general beta.</sentence>
      <sentence position="5" labelers="1, 2, 3">From his post: Desktop Sync is a system tray application that keeps your feeds, folders and read states synchronized between NewsGator Online and the Windows RSS Platform.</sentence>
      <sentence position="6" labelers="1, 2, 3, 4">This means that any application that uses the Windows RSS Platform will be automatically synchronized with your NewsGator Online account!</sentence>
      <sentence position="7" labelers="2, 3, 4">Of course, since IE7 uses the Windows RSS Platform, this is a great way to roam the feeds you read in IE from one machine to another.</sentence>
      <sentence position="8" labelers="1, 3, 4">Check out Nick s postfor information on where to download and where to give feedback on the tool.</sentence>
      <sentence position="9" labelers="1">Pick it up and try it out.</sentence>
      <sentence position="10" labelers="4">Be sure to check out the many other add-ons at IEAddOns.comand let us know what you think.</sentence>
      <sentence position="11">Mark Harris Lead Program Manager - Extensibility</sentence>
    </sentence-list>
  </post>
  <comment-list count="27">
    <comment id="1" author="joe654321" timestamp="2006-09-22 20:00:00.0">New at this so hope I'm blogging correctly...*Internet Explore 7 having a Tab Function is a time saver. &amp;#160;Being able to see a Thumbnail View of all the Tabs on one Tab is a nice feature...*Some web pages have horizontal scrolling information in the lower Status Bar of a Browser but I can't seem to get that to work on..Internet Explorer 7.......</comment>
    <comment id="2" author="Guillaume" timestamp="2006-09-23 19:56:00.0">We would like to test our site with IE7 and make sure it works properly .....Is it possible to install IE7-RC1 on a machine with already IE6 installed on and have the 2 coexist peacefully? &amp;#160;If so, how?....I looked around the MS site but did not find any definite answer to this question. &amp;#160;....Thank you in advance.....Guillaume....</comment>
    <comment id="3" author="shane" timestamp="2006-09-24 07:10:00.0">Something about the name 'gator' and an IE plugin which gets me running for the hills. No thanks.</comment>
    <comment id="4" author="John A. Bilicki III" timestamp="2006-09-24 19:17:00.0">Gator is probably one of the most recognized pieces of spyware if not the most of all time. You should probably change that name.</comment>
    <comment id="5" author="Xepol" timestamp="2006-09-25 13:42:00.0">Gator? &amp;#160;Thanks, but I'd rather download and install the i love you virus than touch any gator product.</comment>
    <comment id="6" author="goose" timestamp="2006-09-25 15:40:00.0">Internet Explorer will tame the gator! IE is the best! TopStyle (Nick's other program) works best with IE! No crappy add-ons to show how it renders! Nick knows IE is best for CSS standards. Microsoft programmers were so smart to have so many programs rely on their advanced rendering engine!</comment>
    <comment id="7" author="EricLaw [MSFT]" timestamp="2006-09-25 18:33:00.0">There's no relationship between NewsGator (which is a big player in the RSS world) and the "Gator" product made by a different company. &amp;#160;It's simply an unfortunate coincidence.....To host IE6 and IE7 on the same machine, use VirtualPC. &amp;#160;VirtualPC is now freely available from Microsoft.</comment>
    <comment id="8" author="Xepol" timestamp="2006-09-25 21:54:00.0">Uh, unfortunately coincidence? &amp;#160;That's a little like walking into McD's and finding Mac-Ecoli on the menu. &amp;#160;Sure, it might be a noodle dish in a cheese sauce, but who's gonna be stupid enough to buy it?....I think you can be pretty sure gator is a cursed product name, because frankly, with all the sleezy tricks that have been played by some companies, there is just no way in hell I'll see "gator" in a product name and believe ANY representation made about it by anyone.....Nope, heck, if I found "gator-begone" afterspray for people in florida, I would be looking for the bluetooth chip in the can waiting to infest any open access point with software that renders your machine the functional equivalent of a doorstop.....So ah ya, "unfortunate"? &amp;#160;- just doesn't seem to cover it for me. You can claim it isn't the same people all you want, I'll just quietly wonder if they just openned a company at arm's length as part of another sleezy trick, WITHOUT anything named gator on my machine. &amp;#160;Thanks.</comment>
    <comment id="9" author="Fduch" timestamp="2006-09-25 22:21:00.0">&amp;gt;with all the sleezy tricks that have been played by some companies....I remember Microsoft suddenly stopped detecting it and said it's not malware :-)....&amp;lt;Little offtopic here&amp;gt;..You think you are rpretty secure when you use IE7? Do ypu know that system security=security of its most insecure component?...."A vulnerability has been reported in Windows XP, which potentially can be exploited by malicious people to compromise a user's system.....The vulnerability is caused due to boundary errors (possibly in "shimgvw.dll") when processing Enhanced Metafiles (".emf"). The problem is that memory is allocated based on size information in the file's header.....This can be exploited to cause heap overflows by specifying a "Size" field, which is smaller (e.g. 1 byte) than the actual size of the file and header. The vulnerability will be triggered by either viewing a malicious file or by navigating to a directory, which contains a malicious file and displays it as a thumbnail.....Successful exploitation crashes "explorer.exe" but may reportedly also allow execution of arbitrary code."....I thought they had troubles with jpg not long ago. Then wmf...Do you think Microsoft learned something from these exploits?..Judge yourself: this vulnerability was disclosed on 2004-02-25...31 month passed.......unpatched...Anyone wants brand new botnet for spam'n'hack?</comment>
    <comment id="10" author="Gareth" timestamp="2006-09-26 03:59:00.0">&amp;gt; To host IE6 and IE7 on the same machine, use VirtualPC....VPC may now be free, but another licence of XP isn't. I find it hurrendous that I have to fork out for an additional licence just to use a web browser!</comment>
    <comment id="11" author="Xepol" timestamp="2006-09-26 05:12:00.0">FDuch -&amp;gt; amazing how few exploits regardless of browser brand and version I get simply because I don't surf to every last free porn site I can find (and avoiding myspace apparently doesn't hurt either).....True, some of those exploits are disturbing in their stupidity, but the OS has never been famous for checking what was actually given to it was valid. &amp;#160;I'm not sure that is actually sleezy so much as negligent.....AS for removing gator apps from their list of spyware, well that was more bad management and litigation avoidance (suing MS is practically an industry unto itself!)</comment>
    <comment id="12" author="hAl" timestamp="2006-09-26 06:01:00.0">The VML exploit is now being abused in combination witrh a zero-day exploit in cpanel which is used by many webhosters...Trough the access of the cpanel leak webistes are infected with a hidden iFrame that exploits the VML vunerability.....</comment>
    <comment id="13" author="ozie" timestamp="2006-09-27 00:25:00.0">hi every one....in my point of view IE7 must have one option in the browser, that cleans all temp files when the browser is close.....delete automatic....that makes IE more secure....best regardes....ozie....Portugal</comment>
    <comment id="14" author="Fduch" timestamp="2006-09-27 12:36:00.0">@Xepol..&amp;gt;Fduch -&amp;gt; amazing how few exploits regardless of browser brand and version I get simply because I don't surf to every last free porn site I can find (and avoiding myspace apparently doesn't hurt either).....I live peacefully withiout AV monitor and firewall...But..It just that those attacks didn't target me...You think that browsing only good sites is enough? You can get the images in mail. +I sometimes saw exploits in ads on good sites. There are many ways to get you exploited...I just wanted to say that MS should treat security more serious.....Researching info on some of unpatched exploit I stumbled upon a response from MS. Some security team discovered very simple heap overflow in SMB, submitted info to MS and tested ProofOfConcept exploit. A response from MS stated that this bug is not serious since "No ProofOfConcept malware using it was found in the wild"!!!..What do you think?</comment>
    <comment id="15" author="hAl" timestamp="2006-09-27 03:29:00.0">Hmmm, an in between update last night for the VML vunerability. Guess the urgency wasn't lost on MS.</comment>
    <comment id="16" author="Paul" timestamp="2006-09-27 09:53:00.0">@goose.."Internet Explorer will tame the gator! IE is the best! TopStyle (Nick's other program) works best with IE! No crappy add-ons to show how it renders! Nick knows IE is best for CSS standards. Microsoft programmers were so smart to have so many programs rely on their advanced rendering engine!"....Chill out dude! you can scream MS is da bomb all you want, but you'll have a very hard time convincing the world that IE is the best for CSS, when every CSS test suite available is to the contrary, even MS admits they have a lot of work to do here.....If you realy do believe that IE is the best at CSS, please provide a URL, where we can see a CSS example, that works as per the spec in IE, but fails in other browsers.....Paul.</comment>
    <comment id="17" author="Silly me" timestamp="2006-09-27 15:16:00.0">How about the ability to pare down IE instead of extend it. &amp;#160;Like, let me trim down the toolbars and icons to only the ones I need. &amp;#160;......</comment>
    <comment id="18" author="John A Bilick III" timestamp="2006-09-27 19:56:00.0">Gator is probably one of the most recognized pieces of spyware if not the most of all time. You should probably change that name...</comment>
    <comment id="19" author="Fduch" timestamp="2006-09-28 05:42:00.0">@Paul wasn't that sarcasm?</comment>
    <comment id="20" author="happy" timestamp="2006-09-28 05:47:00.0">Thanks for This article......welcome to my blog!..http://www.hotproductsreview.net..</comment>
    <comment id="21" author="happy" timestamp="2006-09-28 05:47:00.0">Thanks for This article......welcome to my blog!..http://www.hotproductsreview.net..</comment>
    <comment id="22" author="OffBeatMammal" timestamp="2006-09-28 10:40:00.0">What would be awesome for RSS feeds is having Outlook 2007 and IE7 cross-aware.....A scenario... I subscribe to an RSS feed (say TheRegister.cok.uk) in IE7, and in Outlook. First of all I'd hope they'd be smart enough to share data and not double-dip to download the same stuff twice (don't ask me why I want it in both places, just keep it tidy for me okay!)..If I read an item in IE7, mark it as read in Outlook. And vice-versa. Then... and this would be really cool... if I read the same article directly via the browser... mark it read in both IE7 and Outlook...That's integration and information management ;)</comment>
    <comment id="23" author="Steve" timestamp="2006-09-28 16:28:00.0">@OffBeatMammal....As far as I am aware thats how the Microsoft Feed/RSS API works. It uses a common feed store that apps can use (so on this case, Outlook 2007 and IE7), so the data should be shared.</comment>
    <comment id="24" author="Xepol" timestamp="2006-09-29 22:10:00.0">@Fduch -&amp;gt; Ya, that is definitely a 7 on my stupid meter, and it's boiled all the red outa my negligent thermometer, but that's about it. &amp;#160;....I would like to say that any exploit that depends on access to internal networks is shortsighted, but considering how easy it is to gain access to internal networks with other exploits, that would be shortsighted of ME.....Again, however, I've been on the internet since way back and only seen 1 exploit try to sneak in IE, and then the virus scanner did more harm than good as the hole was already patched and it just went mental overreacting. &amp;#160;My kids, however, are virtual virus honeypots... &amp;#160;I've even considered putting the XP public machine patch on their systems to try to keep it at a minimum, so ya I know any site that draws enough traffic will end up as an exploit host - be it a porn site or the latest pokemon like craze site.....Still, SOME judgement still definitely is a major mitigating factor. (I love some of the stories from the iloveyou virus about how people foolishly opened the mail and ran the attachments...)....I don't hold out hopes that computers will be virus and trojan proof before the people who operate the machines are too.....That said, yes, MS can still be more on top of the problem even if they are improving.</comment>
    <comment id="25" author="Fduch" timestamp="2006-10-01 00:00:00.0">@Xepol totally agree with you</comment>
    <comment id="26" author="OffBeatMammal : Information Overload - a pipe dream!" timestamp="2006-10-28 06:18:00.0">PingBack from http://blog.offbeatmammal.com/blogs/obm/archive/2006/09/28/Information-Overload-_2D00_-a-pipe-dream_2100_.aspx</comment>
    <comment id="27" author="Crash Test Dummy" timestamp="2007-11-22 13:23:00.0">Information Overload - a pipe dream!</comment>
  </comment-list>
</page>

