<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <post author="" timestamp="2006-05-12 09:37:00.0">
    <title>A New Blogfather is Born</title>
    <sentence-list count="15">
      <sentence position="1" labelers="1, 2, 4">Hello everyone, I wanted to let the readers of the IEBlog know that the torch is being passed today on the blog.</sentence>
      <sentence position="2" labelers="1, 2, 3, 4">A fellow program manager, Anurag Jain, is taking over running the day to day activity and moderation duties that keep this blog going on the IE team.</sentence>
      <sentence position="3" labelers="1, 2, 3">You should expect to see posts and comments from him in the future as the official moderator (or Blogfather as we call it) for the IEBlog.</sentence>
      <sentence position="4" labelers="1">Please treat him with the love and affection that you have shown me.</sentence>
      <sentence position="5" labelers="1, 2, 3, 4">:-) Today is my last day at Microsoft after almost nine years of working at the company.</sentence>
      <sentence position="6">I started in 1997 working on IE4 and have spent much of my career at Microsoft working on either IE or MSN Explorer.</sentence>
      <sentence position="7" labelers="1, 2, 4">My wife and I have made a decision to move to the Bay Area, where she grew up, to be close to family and as part of an overall lifestyle change for us.</sentence>
      <sentence position="8" labelers="3">We re both in our mid-thirties now and want to shake things up a bit by moving to another part of the country and experiencing a new life there.</sentence>
      <sentence position="9" labelers="1, 3, 4">My coworkers on IE have been 100% supportive of my making this decision and I still believe that IE7 is going to be a great browser and a real move forward for Microsoft and its customers.</sentence>
      <sentence position="10" labelers="3">It is just time for me to do something different for myself.</sentence>
      <sentence position="11" labelers="2, 4">I want to thank our readers for the comments and the time people have spent on the blog.</sentence>
      <sentence position="12" labelers="2, 3, 4">I ve enjoyed working on it and I ve enjoyed talking to our regular commenters such as PatriotB, Xepol, Fiery Kitsune and others.</sentence>
      <sentence position="13">I m sure that I will still comment here on occasion but I will being doing it in a personal capacity as another IE customer.</sentence>
      <sentence position="14">Thanks!</sentence>
      <sentence position="15">- Al</sentence>
    </sentence-list>
  </post>
  <comment-list count="42">
    <comment id="1" author="Sean" timestamp="2006-05-13 00:59:00.0">Good luck, Al. We will all miss you. :)</comment>
    <comment id="2" author="Nikhil" timestamp="2006-05-12 13:46:00.0">Good luck big boy. What's your next step?</comment>
    <comment id="3" author="AC" timestamp="2006-05-12 13:56:00.0">Seattle to San Francisco isn't really a "shake up". More like.. "a lower latitude".</comment>
    <comment id="4" author="Adam A" timestamp="2006-05-12 14:03:00.0">Good luck, Al. We appreciate all of your hard work with IE, and wish you the best!</comment>
    <comment id="5" author="Al Billings [non-MSFT]" timestamp="2006-05-12 14:16:00.0">Nikhil,.... I am going to be a QA Lead again at a smaller startup in California..... I'm also considering working on a PhD after I finish my current Master's work in Humanities (I start my thesis writing for my MA in a couple of months).</comment>
    <comment id="6" author="Dominic Self" timestamp="2006-05-12 14:46:00.0">Good luck, and thanks especially for your work on the IE section of Microsoft Connect :) You've done a great job responding to bug reports over there.</comment>
    <comment id="7" author="Wraith Daquell" timestamp="2006-05-12 14:50:00.0">Sad to see you go, Al. Good luck on your thesis, PhD, family, etc......And welcome, Anurag Jain!</comment>
    <comment id="8" author="Richard" timestamp="2006-05-12 15:10:00.0">Al. good luck, you did a great work in the IE team.</comment>
    <comment id="9" author="Will" timestamp="2006-05-12 15:14:00.0">Hey,....Ouch, that sucks to see you go.....But I'm sure it's for the best.....Have a great one buddy and see ya around.....Take Care,....Will</comment>
    <comment id="10" author="Soum" timestamp="2006-05-12 15:20:00.0">Wish u all the best Al. Take care. Bye</comment>
    <comment id="11" author="UnexpectedBill" timestamp="2006-05-12 16:04:00.0">Well, good luck in your future plans and doings. It's been an interesting read since I came here a while ago to lobby for a Win2k port of IE7. :-)....(Of course, I'm still planning to read and maybe even comment on what the IE team is up to.)</comment>
    <comment id="12" author="John A. Bilicki III" timestamp="2006-05-12 16:49:00.0">Best of luck to you Al.</comment>
    <comment id="13" author="Fduch" timestamp="2006-05-12 17:02:00.0">Good luck, Al. (-:</comment>
    <comment id="14" author="Verdefruto" timestamp="2006-05-12 17:10:00.0">All goods for you, Al.</comment>
    <comment id="15" author="doglady" timestamp="2006-05-12 18:56:00.0">I worked with a couple up in WA who worked at Microsoft. &amp;#160;They were good friends. &amp;#160;I moved to SF bay area, and I'm glad I did. &amp;#160;I couldn't take the grey days up there, too many of them for me. &amp;#160;I'm in the redwoods now, loving every minute of it. &amp;#160;IE is my favorite, I've tried quite a few, but always come back to IE. &amp;#160;Good luck on your move!</comment>
    <comment id="16" author="Sadowskin" timestamp="2006-05-12 19:25:00.0">Salvator Dali said:.."Goodbye is the beginning of a memory."....We won't forget you wherever you're going...Good luck and thanx for everything!</comment>
    <comment id="17" author="Fiery Kitsune" timestamp="2006-05-12 20:21:00.0">Aw man Al... SAY IT AIN'T SO!</comment>
    <comment id="18" author="Sandi" timestamp="2006-05-12 20:33:00.0">Good luck to you Al. &amp;#160;Enjoy.</comment>
    <comment id="19" author="Xepol" timestamp="2006-05-12 20:50:00.0">Dang, sorry to see you go Al, you helped make this whole process a great experience and made us all feel like our voice was heard and headed!....I look forward to chatting with Anurag in future in the IE blogs, but those are mighty big shoes to fill!....Enjoy the change of life, and I hope it works out for you!</comment>
    <comment id="20" author="PatriotB" timestamp="2006-05-12 23:57:00.0">Wow, had to pick my jaw up twice--one, seeing that you are leaving, and another to see my name signaled out. &amp;#160;Thanks for all of your work, both over the years toward the IE product, and for the work on this blog. &amp;#160;Also, for getting the public bug database up and running.....We'll miss you, be sure to drop in and say hi now and then :) &amp;#160;Best of luck to you in your new endeavors! &amp;#160;And welcome, Anurag!</comment>
    <comment id="21" author="srinivas" timestamp="2006-05-13 01:06:00.0">we all miss you.....any how enjoy the future...</comment>
    <comment id="22" author="Michael" timestamp="2006-05-13 02:26:00.0">Thanks for your hard work!</comment>
    <comment id="23" author="Dean Clatworthy" timestamp="2006-05-13 05:10:00.0">Good luck in all your future endeavours Al :)</comment>
    <comment id="24" author="Nikhil" timestamp="2006-05-13 05:35:00.0">Fantastic Al, good lucky with that. PhD's aren't easy but i'm sure you'll love it!! ;-)</comment>
    <comment id="25" author="Fiery Kitsune" timestamp="2006-05-13 07:05:00.0">(I just realized that I was mentioned in the blog post... I'm one of the less webdev-oriented bloggers, but my expertise is studying the "dark side" of the IE7 beta culture.)....Al Billings, we will all miss you greatly! Rest assured, the IEBlog is safe in Anurag's hands. Good luck in your future endeavours!</comment>
    <comment id="26" author="cooperpx" timestamp="2006-05-13 10:34:00.0">Good luck Al!....I hope everything works out fantastic for you and the Mrs. Thanks for all the hard work and helping to make IE the #1 browser on the planet.</comment>
    <comment id="27" author="hAl" timestamp="2006-05-13 16:01:00.0">Good luck in the bay area Al...Changing the rain for fog I guess ;-)....</comment>
    <comment id="28" author="angelo" timestamp="2006-05-15 00:25:00.0">good luck al and will miss you.Hope happyness follow you and family whereever youre going.bye</comment>
    <comment id="29" author="Viktor Krammer" timestamp="2006-05-15 05:11:00.0">I wish you and your wife all the best. SF Bay Area, California is certainly also a very interesting place to live and work. Good luck!</comment>
    <comment id="30" author="mikx" timestamp="2006-05-15 09:19:00.0">I have been in the position of moving out of a job/company i really liked and where i spent the majority of my career. The song "life of my own" from 3 Doors Down has been the "soundtrack" for that period of my life. Give it a try when you like rock - or just read the lyrics ;)....Good luck for you!..</comment>
    <comment id="31" author="Steve" timestamp="2006-05-15 10:34:00.0">If you are moving to the Bay Area... you might want to check out a small firm in Silicon Valley called Mountain View. &amp;#160;There's a wee company there that is on the cutting edge of Web Development, and "Search". :-)....If you're not sure who it is, try Googling it.</comment>
    <comment id="32" author="name" timestamp="2006-05-15 15:55:00.0">Blogfather -- isn't this a bit sexist? ;-)</comment>
    <comment id="33" author="C'est moi!" timestamp="2006-05-15 20:57:00.0">Now, don't be getting all p.c. on us 'name'! The blogfather is the Godfather...geddit???</comment>
    <comment id="34" author="Mark Reinhold" timestamp="2006-05-17 15:23:00.0">You will like down here. I live about30 minutes east of the City on the Delta in Oakley. It has been Sunny and about 85 all week, so you will have to get used to no rain. but you will get the coldest winter during summer in the City.....Good luck</comment>
    <comment id="35" author="Steve Lamb's Blog" timestamp="2006-05-20 00:00:00.0">OK so this has nothing whatsoever to do with Security but it's Friday afternoon and I want to share with...</comment>
    <comment id="36" author="Wick" timestamp="2006-05-20 01:05:00.0">Goodbye, hello and welcome lol :)</comment>
    <comment id="37" author="donny" timestamp="2006-05-21 00:17:00.0">http://www.iStrology.com/love/?o=833736598</comment>
    <comment id="38" author="Mike Bennett" timestamp="2006-05-22 11:46:00.0">I like the new look, however I don't like the security comment that I have to conitnually click past - "Your security setting level puts your computer at risk". It's very annoying and unnecessary after one or two logins. Can it be turned off?....Thanks.....</comment>
    <comment id="39" author="sdfgsdfg" timestamp="2006-05-25 01:51:00.0">sdfgsdfgsdfg</comment>
    <comment id="40" author="tushar" timestamp="2006-05-25 01:52:00.0">tushar tested this</comment>
    <comment id="41" author="Impressions Scholarcast &amp;#187; Blogfather or blogmaster?" timestamp="2006-06-17 12:36:00.0">PingBack from  http://blog.mrees.biz/myblog/?p=55</comment>
    <comment id="42" author="Betsy Aoki's WebLog" timestamp="2006-06-20 19:01:00.0">Alrighty. So we lose Scoble, we lose BillG (in two years). One of my community mentors, Olivier Ribet,&amp;amp;amp;nbsp;...</comment>
  </comment-list>
</page>

