<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
  <post author="" timestamp="2004-10-28 11:12:00.0">
    <title>Red Sox Win the World Series!</title>
    <sentence-list count="8">
      <sentence position="1" labelers="1, 2, 3, 4">Congratulations to the Boston Red Sox, the 2004 World Series Champions!</sentence>
      <sentence position="2" labelers="1, 2, 3, 4">It is amazing to think that they not only won the World Series for the first time since 1918, but they did it in extraordinary fashion, winning 8 straight games against two of the best teams in baseball.</sentence>
      <sentence position="3" labelers="1, 2, 3, 4">Before I started working with a VIC-20 or a Commodore 64, I was a baseball fanatic.</sentence>
      <sentence position="4" labelers="1, 2, 3">I grew up in New England (Vermont to be exact) living and dying with the fate of the Red Sox.</sentence>
      <sentence position="5" labelers="1, 2, 3">I was fortunate enough to see them play a number of games, cheer for them during the 1975 World Series (they lost to the Cincinnati Reds in seven games), and have my childhood dreams broken by Bucky Dent s home run in the one game playoff in 1978.</sentence>
      <sentence position="6" labelers="1, 2, 3">The Bill Buckner ground ball in the 1986 World Series only served to remind me of the disappointment of my childhood.</sentence>
      <sentence position="7" labelers="1, 2, 3">Now these memories are all the more wonderfully bittersweet with their World Series winning victory last night.</sentence>
      <sentence position="8">Scott</sentence>
    </sentence-list>
  </post>
  <comment-list count="19">
    <comment id="1" author="Ludvig A. Norin" timestamp="2004-10-28 11:38:00.0">America takes it again, that is amazing! Is this like, the millionth time the world series is won by an American team? You tall Americans, you! ;-)....(Congrats though, even here in Sweden it's pretty well known that "Red Sox winning the world series" usually is a joke on the late show).</comment>
    <comment id="2" author="Brady J. Frey" timestamp="2004-10-28 11:47:00.0">Here's to the hope that my Chicago Cubs can be just as successful, and lift their own plague. Congrats Boston!</comment>
    <comment id="3" author="jeffdav" timestamp="2004-10-28 11:53:00.0">Yes, yes, Red Sox.....I am from STL, I am a Cardinals fan.  I thought this was their year.  I was excited.....But who can begrudge the Red Sox their victory?  I would have liked to see the Cardinals win at least one game though...</comment>
    <comment id="4" author="Tony" timestamp="2004-10-28 13:40:00.0">&amp;lt;&amp;lt;America takes it again, that is amazing! Is this like, the millionth time the world series is won by an American team? You tall Americans, you! ;-)....(Congrats though, even here in Sweden it's pretty well known that "Red Sox winning the world series" usually is a joke on the late show). &amp;gt;&amp;gt;....There are two teams in Canada, Ludvig, though one is moving to Washington, D.C. next year.....The bigger joke is the Cubs winning the World Series, and I guess it's the only joke left now...</comment>
    <comment id="5" author="Brady J. Frey" timestamp="2004-10-28 19:25:00.0">&amp;gt;&amp;gt;The bigger joke is the Cubs winning the World Series, and I guess it's the only joke left now...&amp;lt;&amp;lt;....Evil little...:)....But rightfully so -- from cork to fans, we've had our fair share. It's good to see some of the old school teams have made it out of the grave.</comment>
    <comment id="6" author="Dani" timestamp="2004-10-29 12:54:00.0">Seriously, though, why is it called "World Series"? Was that a part of the effort to make it a globally popular game (like that's ever gonna happen with soccer and basketball as competition). I suggest a name change, it sounds almost like Iraqi presidential election, becoming the world champion with no competition from outside...</comment>
    <comment id="7" author="Bruce Morgan [MSFT]" timestamp="2004-10-29 08:05:00.0">From  http://encarta.msn.com/encyclopedia_761563019_1/World_Series.html....The first contests resembling the World Series were held during the 1880s, when the leading baseball clubs of the two major leagues&amp;#8212;the National League and the American Association&amp;#8212;agreed to play in exhibition games following their regular seasons. The name World Championship Series arose during this period, when promoters and journalists sought to arouse interest among fans.....Also see  http://www.snopes.com/business/names/worldseries.asp  for a discussion of why it's not named after the New York World newspaper.</comment>
    <comment id="8" author="Paul B" timestamp="2004-10-31 10:26:00.0">that's commodore 64.  not commadore.....go sox</comment>
    <comment id="9" author="Bob" timestamp="2004-11-01 05:32:00.0">Who gives a damn? What does this have to do with IE???</comment>
    <comment id="10" author="Ralph" timestamp="2004-11-01 06:54:00.0">I am with Bob on this one.  This blog is about IE not a developers stupid fan site.  Don't waste my time any more then you already have.....Go Firefox!</comment>
    <comment id="11" author="borat" timestamp="2004-11-01 08:23:00.0">'world series' - except one country plays it ;)....bob and ralph need to get a life outside of the realm of their computer.</comment>
    <comment id="12" author="Brady J. Frey" timestamp="2004-11-01 09:46:00.0">It's a blog, and their human -- who really cares either way?</comment>
    <comment id="13" author="Dave" timestamp="2004-11-01 13:28:00.0">Borat - I was going to ask if any other country played in the world series (I wasn't 100% sure - I just know England don't) but you beat me to it by answering the question already.....So does anyone know if it's called the world series because anyone can enter, just people outside the US aren't really into baseball or was it just a badly designed name?....If anyone in the world can enter, I think we should get a team together and beat the americans ;)</comment>
    <comment id="14" author="Don't care." timestamp="2004-11-03 00:11:00.0">Who cares?</comment>
    <comment id="15" author="Maurits" timestamp="2004-11-02 15:47:00.0">Hey, turn off the TV and get some work done! ;-)....FWIW, I think there are Cuban and Japanese baseball teams, but I don't think they're eligible to compete in the World Series.  But I'm not sure</comment>
    <comment id="16" author="Yankee Fan" timestamp="2004-11-03 14:38:00.0">Its really sad, three/four generations and only one championship...</comment>
    <comment id="17" author="bill" timestamp="2004-11-05 16:03:00.0">you all need to get a life</comment>
    <comment id="18" author="rachel" timestamp="2004-11-05 17:06:00.0">Can't believe, as was said above that anybody cares. When I saw 17 replies to thia item I expected loads of flames just like this !</comment>
    <comment id="19" author="Liz" timestamp="2004-11-14 17:21:00.0">All of the yankee fans are just jealous! every time one of them says something they think is gonna bring us down it just makes it better because we are reminded of how we beat them! we are the champions and theyre not!!!!!!!!!! GO RED SOX! its unreal. Im still having dreams that it didnt really happen! I live in st.louis but ive been a huge red sox fan all of my life. wearing my boston hat in around St louis and to game was the best. it was so great and suprising how many red sox fans came to st louis to cheer them on! boston has the best fans in all of sports! GO RED SOX!!!YAH!!!</comment>
  </comment-list>
</page>

